<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of lithotomy, or, Of the extraction of the stone out of the bladder written in French by Mr. Tolet ... ; translated into English by A. Lovell.</title>
            <title>Traité de la lithotomie. English</title>
            <author>Tolet, François, 1647-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12350215</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12350215</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 927:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of lithotomy, or, Of the extraction of the stone out of the bladder written in French by Mr. Tolet ... ; translated into English by A. Lovell.</title>
                  <title>Traité de la lithotomie. English</title>
                  <author>Tolet, François, 1647-1724.</author>
                  <author>Lovell, Archibald.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 185, [8] p., [19] p. of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. H. for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lithotomy.</term>
               <term>Bladder --  Calculi --  Surgery.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF Lithotomy: OR, Of the Extraction of the <hi>Stone</hi> out of the <hi>Bladder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>French</hi> by Mr. <hi>Tolet, Lithoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> in the Hoſpital of the <hi>Charity</hi> at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>A. Lovell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Popes Head,</hi> in the Lower-walk of the <hi>New-Exchange,</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> M.DC.LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:2"/>
            <head>To the Ingenious and Expert Chirurgeon, Mr. <hi>Tho. Hobbs,</hi> Lithotomiſt in the Hoſpital of St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Confeſs it is but a weak Apology for my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in prefixing your Name to this Book, to tell you that I can more eaſily ſatisfie the World, than your ſelf in making this Dedication; though indeed it be all that I have to ſay for my ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:59957:3"/>for this Trouble I give you. The truth is, Sir, ſince moſt Books now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days do court, what but a few deſerve, I mean, Protection; as I would not be ſingular in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this Tranſlation without a Patron, ſo I durſt not be ſo unjuſt to the intrinſick value of the Treatiſe, as to ſend it into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> World no other ways provided than with the Credentials of a ſpecious recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the train of ſome
<pb facs="tcp:59957:3"/>great Man, who, perhaps after all, would not admit it into his Family with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your Approbation. It was therefore in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Ingenious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Book, who gave me a Precedent for Dedication, that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the guidance of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and therefore leaſt erring Fame, I was led to your Door, there to leave this Foreign Child, which I have taught to ſpeak (I hope) intelligible <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to be by you diſpoſed of
<pb facs="tcp:59957:4"/>in the World, according as you ſhall think it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, &amp; as you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give it a Character. If it may be able to ſerve thoſe that ſerve you in that Famous Hoſpital, where you ſucceſsfully Operate, or prove Uſeful to any that profeſs <hi>Litho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> that laudable, but difficult and dangerous part of <hi>Chirurgery;</hi> you are in the judgment of moſt men the fitteſt Judge; ſo that the Publick (I make no doubt) will juſtifie my
<pb facs="tcp:59957:4"/>Conduct in ſubmitting it to your Cenſure. But, Sir, how you your ſelf will Interpret this attempt of mine, I dare not affirm; ſeeing Fortune hath not encouraged me to it by intitling me to thoſe free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation &amp; long Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip do allow: However, Sir, I will not deſpair but that the kind Acceptance my endeavours ſhall meet with in the World, will ſo far interceed for me, that what is intended, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:59957:5"/>found to conduce to Publick Good, will not be thought by you to want any private Motives to commend it to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. I ſhall ſay no more, leſt by ſeeming to know you better than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I do, I ſhould ſpoil my own Plea, and appear to be an Intimate Friend, when in reality I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Humble Servant,</hi> A. Lovell.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 23. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59957:5"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF <hi>Lithotomy:</hi> OR, Of the Extraction of the <hi>Stone</hi> out of the <hi>Bladder.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What is meant by <hi>Lithotomy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LIthotomy,</hi> according to the Etymology of the word, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Cutting of the Stone. It had been a more proper way of ſpeaking, to have uſed a term that might have expreſſed the part which is opened by the edge of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59957:6"/>the Inſtrument, becauſe the diviſion or cutting of the Stone happens contrary to the intention of the Artiſt; however I ſhall make uſe of the word <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> which is in vogue, and underſtood by all that are skilful in the Profeſſion. That we may dive into the meaning, and give the definition of the thing; it is an Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Chirurgery, practiſed for the Extracting of Preter-natural hard Bodies which are retained in the Bladder.</p>
               <p>By Preter-natural Bodies is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, all things that are retained within the Body of Man contrary to the ordinary courſe of Nature: And ſeeing ſometimes there are ſeveral things in the Bladder which require the opening of it, we have put in the definition Preter-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Bodies, rather than the Stone; and for clearer diſtinctions ſake, we have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned that <hi>Lithotomy</hi> is only practiſed for ſuch as are hard, and retained in the Bladder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59957:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Obſervations upon the Parts of the Body of Man.</head>
               <p>THE Veſſels and Pores of the Glandules are the uſual Conduits through which the <hi>Corpuſcules</hi> or little Bodies paſs and are filtrated, when their bigneſs and figure makes them fit to be received there; but if there be no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt the Conduit-pipes and the Liquors which ſhould paſs through them, they ſtop: On the contrary, if the Humours have a very rapid motion, they diſtend the paſſages, and many times break them.</p>
               <p>Whatever the impulſe of the Humours may be, their motion abates the more that they communicate it; they make no ſenſible attempt to get out when they are moved on every ſide in a place that can ſtretch and be enlarged to a certain big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the Bladder and the Baſons of the Kidneys: But when the place wherein they are contained is full, if they be not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59957:7"/>evacuated, they are the cauſes of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſeaſes; for the Humours conſiſting of parts of different figure or bigneſs, it follows that ſometimes they cannot glide through one and the ſame paſſage. It is true that Bodies of the like or different extent may paſs through one and the ſame Channel; the contrary is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and may give a beginning to thoſe Tumors, which ſwelling outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly higher than the ſurface of the Body, go by the Name of <hi>Abſceſſes,</hi> after the ſame manner as the internal collections have other appellations: And if the ſame Humours be compoſed of unequal parts, and meet together in a narrow place that is full of windings, ſome of them joyn together, and by their conjunction form a Body that in reſpect of the reſt is ſolid. This Body by its continuance there, and the appoſition of other <hi>Corpuſcules,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more ſenſible to us; it hardens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the rough parts cloſely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another, and the other ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and continue their motion.</p>
               <p>After the ſame manner as it is in Brooks and Rivulets, where the ſmall ſtones
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59957:7"/>ſeparate and retain the Mud; ſo is it in the Glandules through which the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are filtrated: And in the Pipes where Water runs in great quantity, though they be ſtreight, Earth and other Sandy ſubſtances mingled with the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cleave cloſe and ſtick together, and there form a ſtony Cruſt, which in time hinders the paſſage of the Waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Cauſes of the Stone.</head>
               <p>OUR Food liquified is not deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the diverſity of Aliments makes it apparent, that they have parts different in Bigneſs, Figure, and Number; the moſt Nouriſhing, as Jellies and ſtrong Broths have all theſe qualities, ſeeing the Juices of Animals which are the baſis of them are taken from the ſoft and hard parts of the Bodies with which they were aſſimilated, or being ſtill within the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and amongſt the Glandules, tended to that aſſimilation; or from thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that were to be retained or voided,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59957:8"/>by Phyſicians called <hi>Retenta</hi> or <hi>Excreta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other kinds of Food contain alſo parts of a different Nature becauſe Elementary Bodies are mixed, ſo that a ſimple un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt Body is not to be found. The Air wherein we live, and which we breath, is full of little Bodies ſeparated from dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Subſtances, and contributes to our Health and Sickneſs. If then, one breath a thick and groſs Air, if he drink thick and rough Wines that are not fine, mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Waters of Lakes into which ſeveral Brooks empty themſelves, or ſuch as Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie other Bodies, or Snow-water, which contain matters that being frequently drank may leſſen the motion of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; if he eat a great deal of unlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened Bread Water-fowl, Curds, Pap, Old Cheeſe, hard Eggs, ſtony Fruits that are tart and not fully Ripe; as Quinces, Medlars, Pears; if he feed on Beer, Pork, or the Legs and Feet of Animals, Eels, Salt and Spiced Meats; or if he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently make uſe of Medicines which cauſe the more ſubtile parts to tranſpire, as Sudorificks and Diureticks: If he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir himſelf too violently at any time,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59957:8"/>and eſpecially after eating. The long uſe, or the exceſs of theſe things, will be the cauſe of the Stone; as likewiſe too much idleneſs, and ſleeping too long up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the back, becauſe the Earthy parts of groſs Food may meet together in ſeveral places, and diſturbing one another, ſtop the paſſage.</p>
               <p>If thoſe who take the greateſt care of their Health, are not exempted from Living on Food which contains ſlimy parts, as ſtrong Broths, what may we think muſt befall them who to exceſs eat and drink indifferently of all things, or indeed but to Moderation, ſince our Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als participate of a Terreſtrial Matter mingled with a kind of Salt; and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry teaches us, that in the Body of Man there are ſome Juices which diſſolve and liquifie our Food, and others again that thicken it; whence it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that if the one of theſe Liquors by mingling with our Food, renders it fluid; but then being confuſedly hurried away, and conveyed by ſtreighter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, it may be that the ſame Liquor does eſcape, and more eaſily glide away
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59957:9"/>than the Nouriſhment that is retained in, and does Nouriſh the part, or even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, according to the proportion or diſproportion of the Humours which in general may be called Alimentary. It is much the ſame if a Terreſtrial Juice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with the Food after Chylification; for being circulated through all the parts of the Body, if it tranſpire not, it will clog and obſtruct, and many parts of the ſame Nature joyning together, will there produce a Stone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Conſequences that are drawn from the foregoing Chapter, and how the Stone is defined.</head>
               <p>THE Blood is carried to all the parts of the Body; but if its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be more rapid than is uſual, it may diſtend the Capſules and Ureters, and make ſome drops of Blood fall into the Bladder, or other groſs Particles mingled with the Urine, which will then be red, bricky, and gravelly.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59957:9"/>
               <p>People do not always make water ſo ſoon as the Seroſity is ſeparated from the maſs of Blood: If there be a ſmall Stone in the Kidney it may ulcerate it: It deſcends towards the head of the Ureter, and when it is rough or of an exceſſive bigneſs in reſpect of the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſs of the paſſage, it ſtops it, or by the impulſe and force of the Urine that follows, making a great dilatation, it opens a paſſage for it ſelf unto the very Bladder, the patient in the mean time, ſuffering moſt violent Nephritick Colicks, which ſometimes are the cauſe of his Death. On the contrary every ſoft part having a peculiar ſenſe of feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if the Kidneys have no exquiſite feeling, and the Urine or ſmall Stones have by little and little dilated their paſſages, the Glandules will ſeparate and retain but a very ſmall matter, all that was contained with the Blood will paſs through; and as through a Seive, ſeveral ſorts of grain may paſs after that the holes are enlarged, ſo Gravel and little Stones may be conveighed into the Bladder, with the Urine, and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59957:10"/>Patient hardly feel any pain or trouble.</p>
               <p>It is to no purpoſe to alleadge that the dryneſs, or cloſe Union of the parts that compoſe the Kidneys does contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the forming of the Stone; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the Dead Bodies of thoſe that have been troubled with the Stone, it is to be obſerved that the Kidneys are moyſt and ſoft; and it is certain that in living Bodies they are continually moiſtened with ſome Liquor: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it cannot be ſaid that their Bladder is narrow and dry, although Stones are more frequently formed there, than in any other part of the Body.</p>
               <p>It is unjuſt to accuſe our Parents, to make us bear more patiently the pains we ſuffer, becauſe in every body the cauſes of the Stone may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evinced, without imputing them to thoſe to whom we owe our life, and without blaming of them, reaſon may be given, why we ſee Children ſubject to the Stone, whoſe Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers enjoy perfect health.</p>
               <p>We are to conclude that Age and Exceſſes render the parts weak, whoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59957:10"/>Fibres being relaxated give occaſion to obſtructions in Old People, as well as in Children; becauſe the abundance of humidity ſlackens the motion, and the earthy, ſlimy, and ſuperfluous matters, that are not evacuated, occaſion ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſeaſes, as well as the Stone.</p>
               <p>Many diſtempers are bred according to the diverſity of the food that one takes. Thus a man ſhall be afflicted with the Stone, if he feed on courſe food, and which may eaſily coagulate in the Body. There are not wanting ſad inſtances of this; perſons of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Ages, Sexes and conditions, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it, and moſt of thoſe who are troubled with the Stone, and who are to be ſeen in the Hoſpitals of <hi>Paris,</hi> come from the Country, where moſt part of their food is terreſtrial and courſe; and many little Children who live in that manner are cut there.</p>
               <p>Stones are formed in all the parts of the Body, and according to their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions that which ſtops the paſſage takes the name of Sand, Gravel, or Stone: experience confirms this; for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59957:11"/>Stones are found in the Lungs, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the Gall, the Spleen, the Kidneys, <hi>&amp;c. Paraeus lib.</hi> 25. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. reports that he took one out of a mans Knee. Some are found in the Heart: thoſe <hi>which are found in the Nerves</hi> are by <hi>Paulus Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeta</hi> named <hi>nodoſae nervorum concretiones,</hi> knotty concretions of the Nerves. It is likewiſe obſerved that Stony cruſts are formed about the Teeth. I know a man that above twenty years ago voided one by the Navel: it was of the bigneſs of an Olive Stone; and the man is ſtill alive.</p>
               <p>Stones are bred moſt frequently in the Kidneys and Bladder, becauſe theſe parts are appointed for ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and containing the ſeroſity which always carries along with it an earthy Sediment that accompanies the Urine; and the Stones of the Kidneys and Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der give greater pains to the Patient, becauſe they ſtop the emiſſion of Urine; or irritate the parts whoſe uſe is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and the ſenſe more exquiſite than that of many others.</p>
               <p>In a word, we may conclude, that the Stone is a preternatural hard body,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59957:11"/>begotten of the terreſtrial and ſlimy <hi>parts of</hi> our Food.</p>
               <p>We have put in the definition the word ſlimy, to diſtinguiſh it from Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous, becauſe Viſcous things do not harden in a place where there is moderate heat and humidity: but ſuch as are ſlimy, like the White of an Egg, by little and little grow hard, and incorporate with the earthy parts they contain, when they have long continued in luke-warm Liquors.</p>
               <p>This propoſition may be confirmed by the experience of thoſe who render an Oyly and Fat Urine, and who are not troubled with the Stone; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unctuous and viſcous Medicins, ſuch as Turpentine, give eaſe to thoſe that are afflicted with Gravel: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, clear and ſlimy Urine is reckoned among the ſigns of the Stone in the Bladder.</p>
               <p>Authors are divided about the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the queſtion whether or not the Stone be a diſeaſe if all their reaſons be conſidered, it may take the name of a diſeaſe, as well as that of a cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59957:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How Stones are formed and grow in the Bladder.</head>
               <p>THere needs no more but a grain of Sand, or any hard Body to ſerve for a Center or Foundation for monſtrous Stones, which cauſe terror in thoſe that behold them, and moſt frequently death to thoſe from whom they are taken.</p>
               <p>The Sand, and other things that are mingled with the Urine, ſometimes are not wholly voided out, their continuance within gives time to what remains to gather together in ſome place; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that one hath made Water, if there be ſtill in the Bladder a little ſand and ſlimy ſubſtance like the white of an Egg, preternatural heat and the ſeparation and evacuation of the humidity make them joyn together in the ſame manner as the Saline and Tartarous parts of Wine; and the Urine of thoſe that are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59957:12"/>troubled with Gravel which diſtills into the Bladder, being mingled with other Terreſtrial parts, furniſhes matter that joyning with that which remained there before, forms and augments the Stone: Experience informs us that Stones are ſometimes found which are in a manner like a mixture of Sand with the Whites of Eggs, having ſo little Solidity, that one cannot avoid the breaking of them betwixt the Teeth of the Forceps.</p>
               <p>If a little Sand may be the Center or Kernel of the biggeſt Stones, a hard body got into the Bladder and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, may likewiſe be as we have ſeen in an <hi>Italian</hi> Souldier; who to eaſe himſelf of a pain that he felt, thruſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Yard the Tag of a Point about Two Inches long, which ſlipt into his Bladder, and there continued Eight Months. In the Spring of the year 1677, he came to the Hoſpital of the Charity at <hi>Paris,</hi> where without much minding the relation he gave of his condition, I was aſſured by the cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had a Stone in the Bladder,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59957:13"/>he was cut, and the Iron Tag taken out; about which a Stone was form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that hindred not but that it might be ſeen in ſeveral parts. <hi>Parêus, lib.</hi> 25. <hi>chap.</hi> 15. Reports a like caſe. <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Hildanus L. de Lith. c.</hi> 3. <hi>col.</hi> 2. writes that one of <hi>Geneva</hi> having for the ſpace of Twenty Eight years com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the Stone, at length died, and that he was found to have a Stone, the Kernel of which was a Leaden Bullet petrified, which he had received by a Musket-ſhot, and retained all that while. <hi>Joſeph Covillart, Obſ.</hi> VII. of his ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, aſſures us that he had ſeen a Stone, the Center whereof was a Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Bullet which a Gentleman had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Bladder, Five years before he was cut of it.</p>
               <p>I had in cure a young man, who had been cut at the Age of Four years Old, and who was troubled with a Fiſtula: ſince that time he had diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Urine unto the Scrotum, where by degrees a Stone was formed about the bigneſs of a little Pullets Egg, ending in a point like the Stalke of a Pear.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59957:13"/>
               <p>It cannot be determined how long time the Stone is in forming and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that depends upon the conjunction of the parts of the Sand, and the ſudden and quick ſecretion that is made of it in the Bladder: beſides, it may be, the Stone continues at a certain Size, becauſe new Corpuſcles do not always cleave and ſtick to it. I know one that hath had one for ſeveral years, ſeated in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Perineum,</hi> near the <hi>Scro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> without any ſign of dilatation or ſenſe of Pain.</p>
               <p>The growth of Stones in the Bladder happens not without alteration of that part; which becomes weaker according as the Stone increaſes.</p>
               <p>This remark affords us a reaſon why the Bladder of thoſe that are troubled with the Stone is thicker than naturally it ſhould be, which is only cauſed by the debility of the part; becauſe not being able to ſend back the ſuperfluous part of the Blood, it ſwells therewith as the womb in Women when they are with Child, and the parts where there hath been a Fracture, a great Contuſion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59957:14"/>or a Wound; and in the ſame manner as by Suppuration, or the Tranſpiration of Wounds, Fractures and Contuſions, or the Evacuations that happen after a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is brought to bed, the parts return to their natural thickneſs, ſo the Bladder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcharged of the burden that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moded it, and beſides aſſiſted by Medicins and a regular Diet, is reſtored again to its former ſtate. <hi>Bev. c.</hi> 4. <hi>de Cal. Ren. &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſic.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the differences of Stones.</head>
               <p>THE moſt conſiderable difference in <hi>Stones, is in reſpect of their magnitude.</hi> The leaſt Stones of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Three, Four, or Five Years Old, are like great Peaſe; or of the bigneſs of Cherries. Thoſe of Seven, Nine, Twelve to Fifteen Years Old, have them a little bigger. In men grown up, who are of Middle age; and in Old men to the laſt period of life, Stones are found of the bigneſs of a Hens Egg.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59957:14"/>
               <p>I pretend not to determine the exact Size of the Stones of every Age, there is no rule for it; and it is ſufficient to remark what is commonly obſerved; for ſometimes ſmaller Stones are cut from Children and Men, and at other times ſome of ſuch a bigneſs that with relation to the ſubject, they are called Monſtrous.</p>
               <p>The thing contained gives ſometimes the Figure to that which environs it, but Stones rather take than give it. The Bladder, the Urine, or the Preſſure and Juſtling of other Bodies, are the cauſes of many differences; do not we ſee that water hollows Rocks, though it fall drop by drop? It may be obſerved when the Stone is formed by minute Bodies that have Angles, the Urine or the Salt of it blunts the points of them, and the wet Sand not having firmneſs enough, lyes ſlat by the ſides of the Bladder when there is little Urine in it, and forms a flat and ſmooth Stone, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to the Oval Figure of the Cavity of the place, but if the minute Bodies of the Stones are Round, they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59957:15"/>Roll in the Bladder from one ſide to the other; and when they joyn together and are dry, they make rough Stones of a Spherical Circumference, with very great Pores; as is repreſented by the Figures, the Superficies whereof are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal like to Strawberries or Mulberries: On the contrary if they be compoſed of minute Bodies that draw near to a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angular Figure, the contrary will be found, and they will have ſmoother and leſs unequal Surfaces.</p>
               <p>A, B, Gravelly Stones which are the Roundeſt.</p>
               <p>C, D, E, F, G, Stones that have no other name then that of the things they reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; as an Almond, a Hens Egg, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo to be obſerved that there are many more flat Stones ſmooth and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Surface, than round and rough: And this makes it probable that moſt of them are formed of minute Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, the points whereof are blunted.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of assorted kidney stones</figDesc>
                  <p>page 20</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>A</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>B</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>C</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>D</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>E</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>F</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <head>G</head>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
               <p>The Corpuſcles of Stones being ſmall, the Stone will have a fine grain and be more poliſhed and ſmooth, the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles that are bigg and Globular, make the grain courſe, and the Stones ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; becauſe their Pores are full of Urine, or of ſome other very ſubtile matter much lighter than the parts of the Stone; hence it is, that of two Stones of the ſame bigneſs the rougher or leſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59957:17"/>poliſhed ſhall be the lighter, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Menſtruum will Act much ſooner upon thoſe which are Globular and une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, than upon thoſe which are Smoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more poliſhed in their Surfaces.</p>
               <p>When the Stone begins to be formed by Globular Corpuſcles, they are in ſuch ſort diſpoſed, that they contain humidity in their Pores; the Stone in a ſhort time growing in bigneſs, that Water or Humidity is by heat rendered more ſubtile according as the Stone grows harder, and then it acquires a motion that may drive the parts from the Center, and making to it ſelf a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage bigg enough to tranſpire through, but too little to allow an entry to other Terreſtrial Corpuſcles, that Stone will he hollow at the Center.</p>
               <p>Corpuſcles that come neareſt a Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, cement and link the other Particles together; becauſe Triangular and Square Figures, are more capable to hinder motion than <hi>Spherical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Stones whoſe Pores are full of Humidity, are the ſofter, and that ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will be more or leſs, according
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59957:17"/>to the quantity of Aquoſity contained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Center and the Surface; and therefore they are called ſoft Stones if there be much Humidity; and hard, if there be none, and that the parts of the Stone be cloſely compacted. It is certain, the hard are heavier than the ſoft.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Stones are taken out whoſe Center is Globular, and the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face ſmooth; the reaſon is becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Pores of the parts of the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, other ſmaller, and leſs round Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles are placed, and form a ſtony cruſt which has a finer Grain. On the contrary the minute Bodies having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an equal thickneſs from the Kernal, if many Globular Corpuſcles joyn with them before the Stone be hardned, it will be unequal and rough in the Surface.</p>
               <p>If the Stone be formed in the Kidney, and take its grouth there, it will be Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed according to the ſhape of the Cavities wherein its Branches do extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Hence it follows that a Stone formed and augmented in the Neck of the Bladder, will have a Figure Oblong, Cilindrical, or like a Pear, having one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59957:18"/>end ſmaller than the other; but if the Particles begin to joyn higher towards the bottom of the Bladder, it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant but that at the ſame time the Corpuſcles may be ſeparated without touching one another amongſt the Wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles and Rugoſities of the Bladder, and there form Stones which change their place, and which by mutual col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſion become ſmooth; as with two Stones of a moderate hardneſs and a little Water we may make the experiment, and they will have one or more ſides flat, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the figures contained in the little ſpace of the former cut.</p>
               <p>This may ſerve for inſtruction to thoſe who have not ſeen the operation often performed; becauſe conſidering the ſtones, they will be able to judge if there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which are ſometimes uniform, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times unequal in thickneſs. It is rare to find Stones covered with a coat, or ſlimy humor; there are ſome that are ſticking like thoſe which have Prickles and Aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, which are called Gravelly Stones, to diſtinguiſh them from thoſe which are Smooth, Round, or Oval. Some are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59957:18"/>and more ponderous; others are gravelly only in the Center, or in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, ſome are found to be hollow within, and others again ſolid, as in their Superficies differences are likewiſe taken from the Scituation, becauſe there may be Stones in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> the <hi>Perineum,</hi> the neck of the Bladder, the bottom of it, betwixt its Tunicles, in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reters,</hi> the Kidneys, and other parts of the Body. In the gall-bladder ſome are found of a gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh colour; thoſe of the Joints and Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Abſceſſes are Whitiſh and thoſe of the Kidneys and the Bladder are Reddiſh, Grayiſh, Whitiſh or of a colournear to theſe.</p>
               <p>We muſt not forget the number ſeeing it is ſometimes exceſſive, and that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there have been found in People ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Stone to the number of Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Fourty or Sixty ſtones; but the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is not to be limited no more than the bigneſs, becauſe many Stones may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the ſame time, or ſucceſſively, and the fragments that break off from them by grating, produce other Stones; and that is the reaſon that ſome are big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59957:19"/>than others. If a Stone have ſeveral flat ſides, there will be commonly three Stones; there may be alſo more, or only but two.</p>
               <p>Stones that are cut out of Mans body are not ſo ſmooth nor ſo hard as the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Earth; And there are not ſo many adherent Stones as is believed, if you except thoſe that have a coat, or pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles. The ſmootheſt are not extracted without pain if they be large and the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage be not ſufficiently dilated, or if they be not rightly laid hold off by the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, or if the <hi>Membranous</hi> parts be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled through which they are pulled out. It is very hard to judge whether the Stone adheres before the operation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the Diagnoſtick and Prognoſtick ſigns of the Stone.</head>
               <p>IF we reflect on the cauſes of Stones and their differences, we may obſerve the diverſity of their ſigns, of which the Firſt diſcover that there is a Stone, the Second if there be many, and the Third if the effects and conſequences of them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59957:19"/>will be dangerous. The ſigns that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us the Stone or the number, are called <hi>Diagnoſticks,</hi> and thoſe which make us judge of the conſequences, are named <hi>Prognoſticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For facilitating the means to know if the Stone is in the Kidneys and that it deſcends into the Bladder, we cannot cite a better Maſter than <hi>Galen,</hi> book vi. of <hi>Places affec. chap.</hi> 2. who deſcribes the ſigns of the Stone different from thoſe of other Colicks. A ſtraining to vomit, and great and frequent vomitings are much more troubleſome to thoſe that have the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; and then they vomit more <hi>Pitui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous</hi> and Corrupt Matter than thoſe that have the Stone. They are more bound and break no wind neither upwards nor downwards; The Colick ſeems often to move and take up more place, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it encreaſes in diverſe parts; but the Stone Colick torments in the ſame place without intermiſſion. And though pain that afflicts a place higher than the ſcituation of the Kidneys be always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the Colick, yet it does not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that that which is fixed in the region
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59957:20"/>of the Kidneys, is an evident ſign of the Stone; that ſcituation ſignifies nothing at all to diſtinguiſh it, becauſe with theſe marks the Urine muſt alſo be examined. Thoſe that are ſubject to the Stone in the beginning render a clear and pure U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and in the following days ſomething troubled is to be obſerved which ſubſides to the bottom, and at length it becomes all Sandy and Gravelly; which happens not to thoſe who being free from the Stone, are tormented with the Colick, becauſe if they render any groſs excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, one would ſay that there were Flatuoſity in them, and many times they ſwim on the top of the water, being of a Conſiſtency like to the Urine of an <hi>Ox.</hi> Moreover theſe great pains of the Colick are much ſooner eaſed by laxative Gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, than if they proceeded from the Stone. It happens ſometimes that the Colick ceaſes by the voiding of ſome cold humor, and then it is a remedy that not only eaſes but cures and diſcovers the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe: In a word, as the one is cured by voiding of cold Humors, ſo the other is delivered from their diſtemper by voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59957:20"/>the Stone with the Urine, and at the ſame time we may know what part ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers.</p>
               <p>We have ſaid that the Matter of Stones are all kinds of Slimy and Terreſtrial Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances linked together according to the Proportion of more or leſs that forms a hard Body. That Stones forced againſt the ſide of the Bladder, cauſe pain, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, Ulcers, and make one void Purulent matter in the ſame Manner as the Acrimony of Humors, of Urine and Abſceſſes. Little Stones may come out with the Urine: Sometimes they ſtop in the <hi>Sphincter</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra;</hi> they hurt the nerves of the neck of the Bladder which terminate in the circle or crown that is the beginning of the Glans; they may in like manner if they be bigg lay upon and preſs the <hi>Inteſtinum rectum</hi> and cauſe an extraordinary weight, becauſe theſe parts are only appointed by nature to bear the burden of liquid things which are leſs ponderous than the Stone. When they have Aſperities, or are covered with a coat, they are detained in the wrinckles of the Bladder: Now if they be very
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59957:21"/>light, and without adherence, they float a long time in the water; but becauſe of that weight they have they deſcend towards the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and the ſmaller they are in bigneſs or the leſs unequal in their Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, the more they cloſe the paſſage, becauſe the ſmall Stones ſlide eaſily into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and the Urine may run down between the Aſperities of the Stone. That Obſtruction hinders the paſſage of the Urine and obliges the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients to lye upon their backs; they haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with violence turn themſelves, to make the Stone change its ſcituation, that ſo they may facilitate the excretion of the Urine; and becauſe pain makes the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits move towards the neighbouring parts, theſe are ſo diſtended that Men and young Boys are fain to draw out the Yard and Prepuce to appeaſe the pain, and therefore they croſs their Legs, and preſs their Thighs together: Moreover if the Stone change its place a little clear Urine, or mingled with ſlime comes out: According to the ſame principles it may ſtop the paſſage, which obliges thoſe that are ſubject to the Stone to have often a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59957:21"/>deſire to make water. They are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly dry, becauſe the Spirits and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are diſſipated and ſpent by labour, pain and watching.</p>
               <p>By theſe obſervations we may judge that there are ſeveral <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> ſigns which are equivocal, as the Yard and Prepuce drawn out by the hands of the Patient tormented with Inſlammation, pain, and voiding of Purulent matter, by ſharpneſs of Urine and gravel; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sandy matter or little Stones ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſed their ſymptoms, may be evacuated with the Urine; nevertheleſs when that hath a ſediment mingled with Sand and thick Slime, when there is any ſhell of a Stone within, or ſqueezed out of the Yard, it is a pregnant preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which commonly ſerves for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſign.</p>
               <p>The univocal <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> ſigns may be drawn from the ſame obſervations; as a ſudden and fixed pain in the loins to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the one or the other ſide, and ſometime towards both in the region of the Kidneys; after which the Urine looks reddiſh and Sandy, or ſometimes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59957:22"/>Crude, Clear and Watry, a numneſs of the Thigh on that ſide where the pain is when the Stone is bigg: There is a Flit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and reſtleſs Itching towards the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> and in the end of the Yard, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a frequent and ſudden ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Urine, a pain and heavineſs in the <hi>Perinenm</hi> with a continual heat of Urine, and immediately after the making of water a freſh deſire to do it again. It may be obſerved why there are ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtrainings for a ſtool, and why the Urine ſtops all of a ſudden when one is ſtanding, which happens not in another poſture.</p>
               <p>One of the ſureſt of all the <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> ſigns is the thruſting of the finger into the <hi>Rectum</hi> of Men. The Chirurgion will feel a hard body betwixt his finger and the <hi>Pubis,</hi> or a little higher. If the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be not long enough, they make uſe of a hollow Probe called a Catheter, which is introduced through the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> into the Bladder; And then is felt ſomething that is hard making a dry ſound and noiſe as if one touched a Stone; this is the moſt certain of all <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> ſigns.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59957:22"/>It is very neceſſary to make an Experi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of this in dead Bodies, by opening the Bladder, and putting Stones therein; and then having ſtitched up the Parts, to introduce the <hi>Catheter</hi> by the Yard.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Catheters</hi> that are made uſe of, to know if Women have the Stone, are of another Figure; they ſhall be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with thoſe of the other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</p>
               <p>When the Stone is skinned over by a peculiar <hi>Membrane,</hi> or when it is formed betwixt the <hi>Membranes</hi> of the Bladder, or that there be an old excreſcencie of fleſh, called a <hi>Sarcoma,</hi> (which are rare Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers) or if there be a fungous Body, it is not eaſy to diſcern it, becauſe the Symptoms of theſe Diſeaſes in thoſe Parts are much alike; but the Stone is much more frequent there, and one is not often miſtaken, provided he be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive in ſounding or ſearching.</p>
               <p>What we have ſaid of the external Cauſes of the Shapes and Figures, ſerves us for Signs to foretell the plurality of Stones on which we ſee the markes of Colliſion, when during the time of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59957:23"/>Cure, a Stone is taken out which was not left in the Bladder, it is ſaid that Patient hath a Quarry of Stones.</p>
               <p>The figure and bigneſs of the Stone being conſidered after the Operation, one may judge whither or no the conſequences will be dangerous, for if it be monſtrous, the parts have been much dilated and coutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and if it be craggy and pointed, there hath been dilaceration or adherence, and ſome times complication, the Stones that have many aſperities are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo big as thoſe that are even and ſmooth in their ſurface, and that for two reaſons; the firſt is, becauſe the minute Bodies that compoſe thoſe rough Stones, are not ſo cloſely comparted, and ſome of them may break off and be voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Urine; the ſecond, becauſe thoſe aſperities cauſe a more ſudden and pungent pain than other Figures, and force the Patient to betake himſelf more ſpeedily to the Chirurgeon for eaſe, who performs the operation, before that it hath had time to encreaſe to a greater bigneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59957:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> What is to be obſerved by the Chirurgeon before the Operation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HYpocrates</hi> having taken an Oath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to undertake the cutting of the Stone; hath inſtructed us how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is to obſerve all circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in performing it. Wherefore when a Chirurgeon pretends to the cutting of the Stone, he ought to frame to himſelf a Notion or Idea of opening to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a paſſage to the Bladder through a convenient place for extracting of the Stone; by his Rules and Precepts he will know if he can Operate, and then he is to reſolve upon it. He that is troubled with the Stone, is his Subject matter, and it is the duty of a skilful Chirurgeon to foreſee the conſequences, to the end he may guard himſelf with neceſſary remedies againſt the accidents of the matter, and of the Operation.</p>
               <p>A Chirurgeon that is called to ſearch or cut a Patient, ought to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59957:24"/>be diſtinguiſhed from Quacks; this will be eaſie for him to doe, if he obſerve what is taught in the Principles of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgie, where they treat of the Qualities of the Chirurgeon and of the Servants.</p>
               <p>It is one of his chiefeſt qualities to have great skill in Anatomy, that he may know the formation and fcituation of the Parts, that ſo he may Operate with neceſſary circumſpection, being bold but yet not raſh: he ought to make his prudence appear by making his prognoſtick, and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between thoſe things that are inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual and perilous, and thoſe things, wherein according to the Rules of his Art he may ſucceed, without exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the leaſt circumſtances and events that depend not upon him, by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary ſtood of words.</p>
               <p>He is to conſider the State, Strength and Age of the Petient; for knowing that a Man is upon the brink of death, before that he ſearch or probe him, he is to acquaint thoſe that are by, that it is no diſgrace to him if he cannot ſearch him, or if though the <hi>Catheter</hi> be even
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59957:24"/>introduced into his Bladder if he make but little or no Water, by reaſon of his weakneſs; becauſe a Patient falls ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into an apparent ſuppreſſion when he hath no Urine to render: this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to me about 3 Years ago. I was ſent for to ſearch Mr. <hi>Sartorin</hi> an advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, he was very Ancient, Hydropical, and at the very point of Death, and had not made Water for three days: I did not ſearch him, and he died within an hour after I ſaw him: when he was open'd there was not one drop of Water found in his Bladder; his Ureters were ſo cloſed up that the Urine would not paſs.</p>
               <p>The Chirurgeon ought to be Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from the Patients own mouth, and by thoſe that wait on him, of the ſecret matters and diſtempers to which he is ſubject; of the exceſſes that may have contributed to his Indiſpoſition, nothing is to be concealed from him becauſe of the Remedies and Inſtruments which he is to chooſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hypocrates</hi> in the ſixth Aphoriſm of his ſixth Book affirms that old Men are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59957:25"/>hardly cured of the Diſeaſes of the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys and Bladder; and elſewhere he aſſures us that he never ſaw any paſt fifty years of Age Cured; becauſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Caelius Aurelianus,</hi> their Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is Nervous, and they have but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle natural heat; beſides it is ſeated too high, ſo that Medicines cannot be conveighed to it. They are weak, and many Excrements fall continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that way. Nevertheleſs ſeveral have been cut and cured of the Stone at a greater Age.</p>
               <p>It is a good preſage for the Cure, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the operation is performed, if the Patient ſleep, if his reſpiration is equal, his tongue moiſt, and if he be not dry nor do vomit; the lower region of the belly little or not at all ſwelled, with moderate pain and a ſlight Feaver; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in that diſpoſition, (according to <hi>Celſus</hi>) the inflammation ceaſes moſt commonly about the fifth or ſeventh day.</p>
               <p>He ought to know that the Patient oftner dies by the accidents that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie or follow the Operation, than
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59957:25"/>by the Stones whilſt they are in the Bladder.</p>
               <p>If the Patient be too weak, he ought to have time to gather ſtrength, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the Operation would reduce him to evident danger, and the Chirurgion ought to give notice of it, that he may avoid the blame: before the Operation ſome time is to be allowed for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the food that the Patient hath taken, that ſo his Body may be in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plight to endure it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celſus</hi> obſerves that moſt of learned men have a weak ſtomack, and that they are not ſtrong by reaſon of Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and over Studying.</p>
               <p>The Medicines of <hi>Pharmarie</hi> cannot cure the Stone; they only bring relief when the Stones are very ſmall in the Kidneys or Bladder, and when they are as yet but a kind of matter eaſy to be reſolved into Powder, and to be evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Urine. The Chirurgeon ought to make his prognoſtick, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, if he can, the bigneſs of the Stone, with his finger thruſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fundament; informing himſelf,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59957:26"/>how long the Patient has complained of it, obſerving the ſeaſon, place, and other circumſtances directed by the Principles of Chirurgerie.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that have the Jaundice, or Dropſie, are not ſtrong enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Operation.</p>
               <p>When one hath diſcovered the ſigns of the Stone or Gravel, if the Urine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it hath been bloody, or becomes full of purulent matter, it is a ſign that there is an Ulcer in the Kidneys or Bladder, cauſed hy the roughneſs and aſperities of the Stone, and that there is no hopes of curing an Ulcer in the Kidneys, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hot and penetrating Medcines are required for expulſion of the Stones, and the contrary for Ulcers: nature ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtirred up or aſſiſted by diverting Medicines, diſcharges it ſelf of that load, and gives opportunity of eaſing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients of their tormenting pains.</p>
               <p>The Chirurgion ought not to expect a Cure, if after the Patient has been cut, the Nephritick Colick continue long, with pains that are ſometimes heavy and dull, and ſometimes acute and ſharp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59957:26"/>that is a Sign that there is a big Stone, or many little ones, which ſtill remain and take growth in the Kidneys.</p>
               <p>A Patient labouring under a ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Urine, cannot be cured after the third day, if he be taken with a drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie fit, and if he can hardly fetch breath. The Hicket is a mortal ſymptom.</p>
               <p>The Gout happening to thoſe who are troubled with the Stone, may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cure them; the contrary alſo, through the abundance of humors does alſo happen.</p>
               <p>When the Stone is Adherent, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Coat, or if we meet with a fungous or ſarcomatick Body, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of them is gradually to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by injection and moderately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſive Medicines.</p>
               <p>Children are ſooner and more eaſily cured by this Operation, becauſe they have a more ſedate Mind, and leſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Paſſions, being nearer the ſource of Life, than thoſe that are ſtrucken in Age.</p>
               <p>Whilſt all things are preparing, it is the Chirurgions part to comfort the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59957:27"/>ordering likewiſe that he have Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Ghoſtly helps Adminiſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Method of Searching.</head>
               <p>WOmen are leaſt troubled with the Stone, becauſe their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra</hi> is ſhorter, wider, and more direct; and therefore is not ſo obnoxious to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes as that of a Man: but ſeeing all ſorts of Perſons are ſubject to the Stone: having firſt inquired into the Signs, the Patient is to be put in a convenient po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture to be ſearched, that ſo the cauſes of their Pains may be diſcovered. If it be a Woman, ſhe is to be laid upon her Back, her Buttocks a little raiſed, and having choſen a <hi>Catheter,</hi> bending onely at the end, and anointed with Salade-Oyl, or ſome other ſweet Oyl, ſhe is to be made to open her Thighs a little. Then the Operator is to open and ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the <hi>Nymphae,</hi> with two Fingers of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59957:27"/>ſame Hand, that the Orifice of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra</hi> may appear beneath the <hi>Clitoris;</hi> afterward the <hi>Catheter</hi> is to be thruſt in gently with the other Hand, and ſo a ſearch to be made whether there be any Stone or not.</p>
               <p>It is no great matter whether the ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded part of the <hi>Catheter</hi> be turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Pubis,</hi> or the <hi>Vagina,</hi> becauſe of the conformation of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and it is convenient not to be juſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the hollow of the <hi>Catheter;</hi> for fear of the Eruption of Urine.</p>
               <p>For the more eaſie ſearching of Men, they ought to lean a little back, or to be laid upon their Backs; and the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion having made them open their Thighs, he is to raiſe the Yard, and hold it ſtreight betwixt the Thumb, and the fore and middle Fingers of the ſame Hand, Skinning and taking the Prepuce off of the <hi>Glans,</hi> afterward with the other Hand he ſhall gently thruſt an oyled <hi>Catheter</hi> to the very bottom of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> holding it by the end where the rings are, like a Pen betwixt his Fingers, with this difference, that the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59957:28"/>rings of the <hi>Catheter</hi> are be hid with the ſame Fingers, his Hand being half open, turned toward the <hi>Pubis,</hi> and the bending or bill of the <hi>Catheter</hi> towards the <hi>Anus;</hi> then muſt the <hi>Catheter</hi> and Yard be moved towards the Groyn that is remoteſt from him that ſearches, and in the mean time he is to turn betwixt his Fingers the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and the bill of it towards the <hi>Pubis.</hi> Obſerve that the fore and middle Fingers touch the <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> on the one ſide, and the Thumb on the other, anſwering exactly to the ſpace betwixt the Fingers; at the ſame time the Chirurgion is to preſs a little more with the fore Finger, which is higher than the middle Finger, ſo that the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the motion be upon the Thumb; by that means the handle of the <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is covered, and the bill or bending of the <hi>Catheter</hi> raiſed, that it may preſs the <hi>Sphincter,</hi> and enter into the Bladder; this is the Figure of it.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 44</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Sometimes, when the <hi>Catheter</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced to the very bottom of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> and when the bill of it is turned towards the <hi>Pubis,</hi> the Chirurgion is obliged to let go the Yard, and to put a Finger into the <hi>Anus,</hi> and by a light compreſſion of the <hi>Vectum,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> the <hi>Catheter</hi> is conducted into the Bladder; which being done, he is to draw out his Finger, and hold the Yard no longer.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Wire</hi> or <hi>Stilet</hi> is taken out of the <hi>Catheter</hi> before it be introduced, and when it is in the Bladder, it is held by the rings betwixt the fore and middle Fingers, having the Thumb upon the hollow of the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and the back of the Hand turned towards the Patients Belly: then the Chirurgion is to give ſome eaſie Jogs, moving the bill a little to the right and left, without turning the <hi>Catheter</hi> fully round. The rings are lowred, that the bending may mount towards the bottom of the Bladder, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59957:30"/>ſometimes they are inclined near the Belly, without forcing the <hi>Catheter</hi> out of the <hi>Sphincter,</hi> and by theſe kinds of motion, if one be very attentive, when it is a Stone, one ſhall hear a little ſound as of two ſmall Stones that touch one another, or at leaſt ſomething is to be felt that makes a colliſion with the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theter,</hi> as if it were rubbed with a Stone, if it float, it may be felt when there is Urine in the Bladder; And that requires that the Operator ſhould ſtop the hollow of the <hi>Catheter</hi> with his Thumb; but if nothing be felt, the Urine is to be let out by the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and then diligent ſearch to be made.</p>
               <p>There is another way of ſearching Men; the Yard is to be raiſed and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately pulled up, laid upon the Groyn, and the rings of the <hi>Catheter</hi> inclined towards the Belly; ſo that the bill be turned towards the <hi>Anus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are Ungoſities in the Bladder that ſometimes deceives him that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; but they may be diſcerned, becauſe then, one finds onely ſomething that is ſoft or but moderately hard, which makes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59957:30"/>no noiſe by the touch of the <hi>Catheter,</hi> the Bladders of Children have no Ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities like to thoſe of Men.</p>
               <p>In the Hoſpital of the <hi>Charity</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> about the beginning of a cutting in the year, 1681. Two Children were preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be cut; but the Stone not being felt, they were put to Bed again; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, after many others had been cut, they were examined the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, the Stones diſcovered, and immediatly cut out, becauſe they were prepared. This makes it appear that one ſhould not be too haſty to give his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, if ſometimes the Stones are not felt though the Signs ſeem evident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may be ſmall or change their place. At the ſame time a Man was ſearched with a <hi>Catheter,</hi> uſed to make Patients void Urine. After that the bill had been inclined to the right ſide, and ſeveral times thruſt towards the bottom of the Bladder, the rings were preſſed down towards the Belly, as if there had been a deſign to bring out the <hi>Catheter;</hi> but when the bill of it was judged to be near the <hi>Sphincter</hi> of the Bladder, it was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59957:31"/>turned to the left ſide, which could not have been done ſooner, becauſe of the length of the bending of that <hi>Catheter,</hi> and the ſmalneſs of the Bladder; the Operator continued to ſearch the Stone, which not being felt, was found with another <hi>Catheter,</hi> whoſe bill from the beginning of the bending, was not ſo long, and therefore that <hi>Catheter</hi> turned eaſily in the Bladder.</p>
               <p>This obſervation inſtructs us what <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theters</hi> are to be choſen for voiding of Urine, whoſe bill ought not to be ſo long as thoſe that ſerve for making of the inciſion, and which are Channelled or Furrowed. There are ſome Men who have very narrow <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra's,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſmall <hi>Catheter</hi> like thoſe for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and of a ſufficient length. <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> that do not eaſily bend or bow, are likewiſe to be choſen; and that depends on the Work of the Artiſt that makes them.</p>
               <p>When the Stone is in the Neck of the Bladder, it is not neceſſary that the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theter</hi> ſhould be introduced ſo far as the bottom of it, becauſe the Stone may be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59957:31"/>felt, provided the <hi>Catheter</hi> be onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced as far as the bottom of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When there is a Carnoſity, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the <hi>Catheter</hi> to ſlide into the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Operator muſt put a finger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>rectum,</hi> and if there be a Stone he will find a hard and ponderous Body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Pubis,</hi> if there be a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, it is the opinion of <hi>Fernelius,</hi> that no ſearch ſhould be made; in that caſe one ſhould obſerve to ſearch gently and ſeldome, becauſe otherways it may be the cauſe of pain, inflammation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriation, a gangrenous Ulcer in the <hi>Sphincter,</hi> nay and even a Supreſſion of Urine, or a peircing of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides theſe Diſeaſes, one cannot ſometimes ſearch becauſe of a <hi>Phymoſis,</hi> and of a Stone in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be ſaid as to that, as much as is neceſſary to be known upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Lithotomy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59957:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of a <hi>Phymoſis,</hi> and of the Stone in the <hi>Urethra.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAny Children have a <hi>Phymoſis;</hi> to ſearch them, we muſt hold the Yard betwixt the little finger and the ring finger, the back of the hand being towards the Belly, and with the other fingers pull back the <hi>Prepuce,</hi> as if one intended to skin the <hi>Glans,</hi> the thumb on one ſide, and the fore-finger and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-finger on the other, gentlely preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with theſe three fingers towards that part of the Nut or <hi>Balanus,</hi> where one Judges the end of the <hi>Glans</hi> to be ſeated, that by that means the Orifice of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> may be the more dilated; then the <hi>Catheter</hi> is to be entroduced gentely, ſearching for the perforation of the <hi>Glans;</hi> one may know that he is in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> if the <hi>Catheter</hi> enter eaſily, and by feeling with the fingers of the other hand along the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> on the under ſide of the Yard.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59957:32"/>
               <p>If the <hi>Prepuce</hi> be ſo ſtrait that the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theter</hi> cannot be introduced, or if one cannot hit upon the Orifice of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> there is no danger, to dilate a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the <hi>Prepuce</hi> ſideways, with the point of a common <hi>Biſtori</hi> or a pair of ſharp Ciſſars.</p>
               <p>Obſerve that before the introducing of the <hi>Catheter,</hi> it will be fit to ſqueeze the yard with the fingers along the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and ſo to try if one do not feel ſome hard Body which ſtops the paſſage, as Carnoſities or Stones. When it is a Stone the <hi>Catheter</hi> is to be drawn out; and if before ſearching it was known to be a Stone, and that it ſtuck in the middle of the Yard between the <hi>Glans</hi> and the <hi>Teſticles,</hi> there is no ſearching, but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely preſſed the Yard with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the <hi>Pubis</hi> to the Stone, the Operator ſhall take a <hi>Curette</hi> or <hi>Extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or</hi> oyled, and having introduced it by little and little, and paſſed it beyond the Stone, he may therewith draw it out of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Curette</hi> or <hi>Extractor</hi> is like an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picker, made of Steele, becauſe it is leſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59957:33"/>apt to bend than if it were made of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Metal, the Operator muſt have of them of ſeveral ſizes in bigneſs, four or five inches long; the figure of it you may ſee in the lower end of the ſecond plate of Inſtrments.</p>
               <p>The extremitiy of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> may be dilated in the upper part of the <hi>Glans,</hi> when ſtones are extracted with the <hi>Curet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> and when being brought as far as the Orifice, they cannot paſs without pain.</p>
               <p>The Urine ſerves for a Remedy; and if there hath been a Contuſion and Pain, it is enough to foment the Yard with the oyl of Roſes, and cover the Nut or <hi>Balanus</hi> with a little pledget dipped in the lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Arceus,</hi> diſſolved with a little <hi>mel raſatum</hi> moderately expreſſed out with the <hi>Nucial</hi> or Croſs bandage open in the middle, and the band with three heads to wrap it up in, and it is not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, if there be need for it, to put a girdle about the Child, to which the band may be tied, nay and a Collar hanging about the neck like a Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Strap, the lower part of which is to be faſtned to the girdles that it may
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59957:33"/>not ſink lower than one would have it.</p>
               <p>That Bandage ſerves for other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the Yard, begininng to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it upon the <hi>Glans,</hi> and then bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it nearer to the Belly, with ſlight coulings and circumvolutions to keep the Medicine faſt to the part, and near to the <hi>Pubis</hi> an indifferent hard knot is to be caſt, then the two heads at the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of the Band or Truſs are to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ied to the girdle.</p>
               <p>The preciſe length and breadth of all the parts of that bandage cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, becauſe it depends upon the Judgment of the Chirurgeon to make them ſo long and ſo narrow as that they be not Cumberſome.</p>
               <p>There is ſtill another way of extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Stone out of the Yard, when it is at a diſtance from the Sphincter of the Bladder. And that is this; having drawn back the skin of the <hi>Praepuce</hi> as much as one can towards the Nut of the Yard, Ligature is made betwixt the Stone and the <hi>Pubis;</hi> or otherways one may with the fingers compreſs the Yard and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kin be fore and behind the place where
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59957:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59957:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59957:35"/>the Stone is obſerved to ſtick, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward make Inciſion upon the Stone a little ſide-ways in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> that ſo the Stone may be taken out by means of the <hi>Curette</hi> or Extractor, introduced into the Orifice of the Inciſion, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature being removed and the Skin loſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Inciſion ſtops and is cured by the Balſom of the Urine; without other Medicine.</p>
               <p>If one be unwilling to make Inciſion in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> or if the Stone cannot be got out with the Extractor, it will be fit to give <hi>Diuretick</hi> Medicins to force it forwards to the <hi>Glans</hi> thereby to facilitate its Extraction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the time of Searching and Cutting; of the Inſtruments; of the patients Diet; and of the firſt Preparation.</head>
               <p>A Patient may at any time be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or probed to make him render his Water, and to diſcover the Diſeaſe;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59957:35"/>if one find himſelf extreamly troubled with the Stone, cutting is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed without danger; but ſince ſome diſeaſes requires a ſpeedy Operation, we ſhall not ſpeak of the time which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the time of neceſſity; but onely of that of Election, which is laid hold of, when the diſtemper is in ſuch a Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as to give opportunity to do things in order and without precipitation.</p>
               <p>The Spring is the moſt temperate ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Year; wherein <hi>Vitriol</hi> the father of all Productions, gives verdure to Plants, and contributes to the vigour and ſtrength which men find renewing in themſelves at that time, then do men undertake what was interrupted by the exceſſive cold or heat of other ſeaſons, that in the <hi>Atumne</hi> they may enjoy the fruit of their paſt labours. With great reaſon then men chooſe the Spring time for many Operations, and amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for <hi>Lithotomy.</hi> In this Conutry we muſt expect till the impreſſion of the Winter cold, and the frequent Rains be over. Though the Spring begins on the eleaventh of <hi>March,</hi> nevertheleſs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59957:36"/>to the temper of the Air, the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Stone is accelerated or retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but commonly it is performed in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> Next to the Spring, the <hi>Autumne</hi> is to be preferred before the other ſeaſons.</p>
               <p>Though Liquors and <hi>Menſtruums</hi> for diſſolving of Stones were in uſe, yet muſt we of neceſſity ſpeak of the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Chirurgery, which are Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Iron or other Metalls proper for <hi>Lithotomy.</hi> Take here their figures and the names of their parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Raſor to ſhave off the hair from the privy parts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Common Cizars for ordinary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Hollow ſound or probe, called a <hi>Catheter,</hi> for ſearching of men, and making them render their Water, and its <hi>Stilet</hi> or Wire to cleanſe it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A <hi>Catheter</hi> or <hi>Staffe</hi> for making Inciſion in men, furrowed in the back from A. which is the bill or <hi>bec,</hi> to the place marked B. without any cavity in its length.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of surgical instruments</figDesc>
                  <p>page 56</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>conductor</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>forceps</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>male dilator</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>female dilator</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>dilator</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>hook</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>scoop</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>cannula</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>languette</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>wound dressing</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>curette</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of surgical instruments</figDesc>
                  <head>page. 56</head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>razor</figDesc>
                     <head>1</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>scissors</figDesc>
                     <head>2</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>catheter</figDesc>
                     <head>3</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>catheter</figDesc>
                     <head>4</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>hollow catheter</figDesc>
                     <head>5</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>straight catheter</figDesc>
                     <head>6</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bistoury</figDesc>
                     <head>7</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>languette</figDesc>
                     <head>8</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bistoury</figDesc>
                     <head>9</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>probes</figDesc>
                     <head>10</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>conductor</figDesc>
                     <head>11</head>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
               <p n="6">6. A Streight <hi>Catheter</hi> or <hi>Staffe</hi> and hollowed or furrowed from the bill to the place marked C. which is ſometimes made uſe of for making Inciſion at the Orifice of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>retha</hi> of Women. It is requiſite to have always in the <hi>Catheter</hi> caſe a part, a little piece of a Spunge moderately moiſtened with Salad-Oyle, becauſe ſometimes it may be wanting when there is need of it to anoint the <hi>Catheters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. A <hi>Biſtori</hi> that opens like a Lancet with a point and edge like the ſame one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the point blunter, at the head where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is a flat tayle to keep it firm againſt the handle when it is opened,</p>
               <p n="8">8. A <hi>Languette</hi> or roller to mount the <hi>Biſtori,</hi> it is ſlit at the end, a finger broad, and a foot and half long.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A <hi>Biſtori</hi> mounted, that is to ſay, armed with the <hi>Languette</hi> or Roller.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Conductors or Probes, whereof a pair ſerves for the Operation, that which is next to the <hi>Biſtori</hi> mounted is forked, and the other has a line in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59957:39"/>length of its cavity, for guiding and conducting the former. Nevertheleſs that alone which is remoteſt from the <hi>Biſtori</hi> may be uſed for conducting the forceps or <hi>tenette.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Another kind of Conductor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of the two above deſcribed; it turns with an elbow about the midle, and has a Spring betwixt the branches near the rings; it was invented by <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Covellart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Another kind of Conductor cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in French a <hi>Gorgeret</hi> more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and more in uſe. It is hollow ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and grows narrower at the end, where there is a bill that is introduced into the furrowing of the <hi>Catheter,</hi> whilſt it is held by the other end ſhaped like a T. There are ſome who doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of this Conductor, ſaying that it dilates the parts too much, and that it occaſions Fiſtula's, but without ground, for it is narrower than the forceps which is drawen out with the Stone and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more room, and the Fiſtula is onely occaſioned by the conſequences of the Operation, as ſhall be explained in its proper Place.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:59957:39"/>
               <p n="2">2. Sreight and crooked <hi>Forcipes</hi> or <hi>Tenettes.</hi> A. their Teeth, B. their Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, C. their Rings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A <hi>Dilatatory</hi> for Men. It is named a Compound or great <hi>Dilatatory.</hi> D. the bill or <hi>bec</hi> of the <hi>Dilatatory.</hi> E. the handle.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A ſimple <hi>Dilatatory</hi> for Women. The extremities of it are blunt, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall, the Branches are joyned in ſuch a manner that cloſing the one end, the other opens. It repreſents the letter X.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another <hi>Dilatatory</hi> that may ſerve for Women and little Boys. It hath a ſpring near the handle, and can dilate but moderatly. It may be uſed when one fears that ſome <hi>Fibres</hi> have been left in time of the Inciſion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Hook or <hi>Crochet</hi> to pull out the Stones that are in the Paſſage, either in the leſſer Operation or otherways, ſome cauſe them to be made with little Teeth in the cavity of its bending; but there is no neceſſity for it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. A Button, a Scoope. About ten Inches long, and as big as a quill. F. the part properly called the Button. G. the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59957:40"/>body of the Button, H. the other end which is hollow, called the <hi>Curette</hi> or Scoop of the Button. I. a ſlight line to conduct the Forceps.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A hollow Tent, Pipe or <hi>Canula,</hi> having rings at one end called the Head, the other end is called the Point, where there are two holes called the eyes of the Tent.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A <hi>Languette</hi> or Fillet for mounting the hollow Tent, introducing it into the Slit, and putting the two ends of the Fillet through the rings of the Tent, then it is called a Tent mounted. That Fillet or <hi>Languette</hi> is to be two foot long, and a finger broad.</p>
               <figure>
                  <p>page 62</p>
                  <figDesc>depiction of medical and surgical supplies</figDesc>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>tourniquet</figDesc>
                     <head>1</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bolster</figDesc>
                     <head>2</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>plaster</figDesc>
                     <head>3</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>compress</figDesc>
                     <head>4</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bandage</figDesc>
                     <head>5</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>truss</figDesc>
                     <head>6</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>pledget</figDesc>
                     <head>7</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>plaster</figDesc>
                     <head>8</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>plaster</figDesc>
                     <head>9</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bolster</figDesc>
                     <head>10</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>compress</figDesc>
                     <head>11</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>tourniquet</figDesc>
                     <head>12</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>bed</figDesc>
                     <head>13</head>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
               <p n="11">11. An Extractor or <hi>Curette</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting Stones out of the Yard.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Chair uſed in the Hoſpital of the Charity at <hi>Paris,</hi> on which the Patient is ſet, for the more commodious performing of the Operation. There are behind two bars or rods of Iron in form of Butte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes; they are hooked, that ſo they may enter into the rings of the Chair, and ſharp at the end to ſtick firmer in the Floor, becauſe the Patient ſtruggles and uſes violence in the time of the Operation. The Chair ſhould be placed a little obliquely for the light to come upon the right hand of the Chirurgeon, that he may ſee the better when he is about his Operation.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of that Chair, the Patient may be ſeated upon the ſide of a Bed, or on a Table, with a Mattreſs or Quilt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one part covers the back of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chair reverſed, about half a foot diſtant from the edge of a Table, in a ſloaping manner. That Chair is to be made faſt with many ſtrong cords, if there be no Mattereſs or Quilt, it will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59957:42"/>be ſufficient to lay a Pillow or any other thing to make the place ſoft, and a fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Sheet over it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Sheet folded length-ways with many folds, to cover the Chair that hath been deſcribed, or the Mattereſs in the time of Operation: one part of it is before, and the reſt hangs behind.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Budget to put in ſeparatly the ſtreight Forcipes in the one ſide, and the crooked, with the hook in the other, in the bottom the <hi>Dilatatory,</hi> the Button and the Conductor are hid. It may be ſhut, lifting up the ſides of it where there are Button-holes, into which are put the Buttons that are faſtened to the places marked C. D. near the ſtrings.</p>
               <p>A Table whereon the Porringer with Oyl is ſet, and the mounted Biſtoris laid, under which a peice of linnen-cloath folded with many plaits, is put croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, that their points may not touch any thing. It is fit that ſeveral Biſtories ſhould be mounted, though there be but one Operation to be made, becauſe the edge or the point are ſometimes blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and it is neceſſary to have ſome
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59957:42"/>rags of linnen-cloath and napkins in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs.</p>
               <p>All the Inſtruments may be made of Steel or Iron, nevertheleſs the <hi>Catheters,</hi> Conductors, Button and Tents, are neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er when they are of Silver, and leſs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ruſt. Of each kind there ought to be ſeveral ſizes, and thoſe well po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               <p>It is not enough to have ſpoken of the Inſtruments of Chirurgie, we muſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, according to the Rules of good method, take into conſideration, what things are neceſſary before, in the time, and after the Operation. Before the Operation the Patient ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſome days by a Diet, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting, Glyſters, Purges, reiterated more or leſs, according to the advice of a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſitian; and the night before the Operation, the Patient muſt take a laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or elſe an aſtringent Glyſter, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as need ſhall require. He muſt have a days time at leaſt to reſt in after he hath taken Phyſick: and ſpiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midies are not to be omitted.</p>
               <p>At the time of cutting, the Operator
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59957:43"/>muſt chooſe four faithful ſervants at leaſt, a Chamber indifferently warm, and in a good Air where the light of day may ſuffice. He muſt have an Apron and Sleeves, and under the Table a tub of warm water to waſh the Inſtruments; upon the Table there muſt be Salad-oyl or oyl of Roſes, and there he is to lay his Inſtruments in order for the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: all theſe things are called the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives. <hi>(Appareil)</hi> for the Operation: the Bandage and Medicines that are made uſe of to dreſs the Patient that is cut, are called the preparatives for the dreſſing, which ought to be in readineſs, becauſe they are uſed immediatly after the Operation.</p>
               <p>The Medicines, both Powders and Oyntments ought to be aſtringent, warm, <hi>Oxycrat</hi> and <hi>Oxyrodinum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Bandages as well for Men as Women. are
<list>
                     <item>1. The Ligature, or <hi>Colier,</hi> which is a great band for Blood-letting, when the two ends of it are tied together, it is of an oval Figure, which is put over the Head, and comes down as far as the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59957:43"/>This band may be put about the Patient before the Operation.</item>
                     <item>2. A Bolſter or compreſs of a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thickneſs, three or four fingers broad, to put upon the wound when the Operation is done, and when the Patient is to be carried to bed; it ought to be laid upon the Table, with the Biſtories and the <hi>Catheters.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. An aſtringent Plaſter of a ſufficient bigneſs to cover the Belly.</item>
                     <item>4. A <hi>Ventriere</hi> or Belly-clout, which is a great Bolſter or Compreſs to cover the Belly, it is to be dipped in warm, <hi>Oxycrat.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. The <hi>Froude</hi> or Bandage or Truſſe with four Heads, A. the Heads which may be called Twins, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the ſame place, and are deſtined for one and the ſame uſe.</item>
                     <item>6. The Truſs or double T. or ſecond Truſſe, B. B. the girdle of the Truſs, C. C. the Tailes or Straps of the Truſs.</item>
                     <item>7. A Pledget <hi>Plumacean</hi> covered with Aſtringent.</item>
                     <item>8. Aſtringent-Plaſters of ſeveral ſizes.</item>
                     <item>9. A Plaſter longer than broad, to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59957:44"/>be put ſome days after the Operation upon the Pledget inſtead of the former Plaſters, this Plaſter ought to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what longer than the Wound.</item>
                     <item>10. A ſmall ſquare Bolſter or Compreſs indifferently thick, and ſomewhat larger than the Plaſter above deſcribed.</item>
                     <item>11. Another double compreſs an Inch broad and a Foot long for Males, called a Truſs. Theſe two Bolſters are to be moiſtened in war m <hi>Oxycrat.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>12. A Ligature or <hi>Farettiere,</hi> which is a long band to be Swathed about the Thighs, that the Patient may keep them within a moderat nearneſs to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
                     <item>13. A Bed covered with a Rowling-Sheet, or a Sheet doubled into many folds, and laid croſs the Bed, in the place where the Kidneys and Thighs of him that is cut do Reſt. There is need of ſeveral Sheets or <hi>Alaiſes</hi> to ſhift and make it dry when it is wet, it is to be warmed with a Warming-Pan; if it be needful, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite alſo to have a good many Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins in Readineſs to put under the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, when he hath a Looſeneſs that he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59957:44"/>may be the ſooner laid dry, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beſides that Sheet a Sere-Cloath or thin Blanket is put betwxit the Sheets &amp; the Quilt to preſerve it from ſpoiling and rotting by the Urines; but a Sere-Cloath makes the Bed too hard, and is not good but when there is a want of Sheets or a Quilt to ſhift the Patient. It is not to be forgot that a cord muſt be faſtned to the top of the Bed or ſome other place to help the Patient to raiſe himſelf.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>There are ſome Operators that hide their Inſtruments in their pockets, or put the <hi>Catheters</hi> in their Button-Holes before they anoint them with Oyle; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lay them in a Diſh, nevertheleſs ſeeing it makes a noiſe when the Oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator takes them up to Operate with, it ſeemes more commodious to have them in a Pouch or Budget.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59957:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Poſture and Scituation into which Children are to be put; when they are to be Cut.</head>
               <p>ALL things being prepared, the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theters</hi> put into Oyle, the <hi>Biſtoris</hi> and Tents mounted, and laid upon the Table, the Tub with warm water un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath it, the ſtreight and crooked Forcipes with the hook placed in order in the fore part of the Budget, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor, the Button and Scoop, and a Dilatatory, if it be thought neceſſary in the bottom of the Pouch or Budget: the Patient is ſent for, brought to the place of Operation, and ſet upon the Chair ſtanding a little obliquely, that the light from the Windows may dart upon the right ſide of the Operator, who is to keep his Inſtruments from the ſight of the Patient.</p>
               <p>If it be a Child of four, five, ſeven, ten or twelve years of Age, two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may hold him by the Hand and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59957:45"/>Feet on each ſide, whilſt another get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up upon ſomething behind the Chair, and looking forwards, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly lean upon the Patients ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, placing the Thumb of both Hands towards his Back, and the other Fingers upon the Clavicles, for the ſurer hold, the Servant who is on the right ſide of the Patient, ought to put his left Hand betwixt the Patients Thighs, and take faſt hold on his right Hand wriſt, and that the Child be not hurt, the ſleeve of his Shirt may be pulled down to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Hand; after that the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with his Right-Hand ſhall lay hold of the Leg on the ſame ſide by the Foot and Anckle. The Servant on the Patients Left-Hand ſhall do the ſame, taking hold of the Left-Arme with the Right-Hand, and with the Left-Hand of the Left-Leg near to the Foot.</p>
               <p>In this poſture the Childs Hands muſt almoſt touch his Heeles, and if he but any way hold faſt, his Thighs ſpread, the <hi>Lithotomiſt</hi> has Room to Operate, and becauſe Children do extreamly Struggle and Strive, two other ſervants may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59957:46"/>keep their knees a ſunder; but it is cheifly to be obſerved in this poſture, that the Patient lean half backwards accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſhape of the Chair, or for want of that, near the Beds ſide, or the Table, covered with a Quilt or Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs, ſo that his Fundament may be ſeen, and that his Feet do not reſt upon any thing, ſo that he have leſs force to ſtir or move himſelf. Hear is the Figure of it.</p>
               <p>There are ſome Operators who chooſe a ſtrong Man, and make him ſit upon a pretty high common Chair, or upon the end of a Bench, who having a Cuſhion againſt his Belly, and a Sheet over it, takes the Child, who is to be cut, upon his Knees joyned together, the Man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Knees cloſe, puts his Hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Childs Legs, and ſo takes hold of his two Wriſts; by this means the Child is put into a convenient poſture to be cut, take here the Figure of it.</p>
               <p>Beſides the Man that holds, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that ſome other perſons lean up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Childs Shoulders, open his Knees, and keep his Feet ſteddy.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 70</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:47"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 70</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:48"/>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:59957:48"/>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, ſeeing the Operation is ſometimes laborious, and that the Man who holds may be weary, it is better to make uſe of the firſt way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the different ways of Extracting the Stone, according to the Cuſtome of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The Practice of the high Operation</head>
               <p>SOmetimes the Chirurgion cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the furrowed <hi>Catheter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of pain or inflammation, occaſioned by too frequent ſearching before, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there may be fear of putting the Patient to too much pain, or that there may be a Carnoſitie or Calloſitie in the Part, or becauſe the Stone is in the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum,</hi> or in the Neek of the Bladder.</p>
               <p>Theſe different diſpoſitions oblige the Operator to conſider how and in what manner the Operation is to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The firſt which is not in uſe, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59957:49"/>the high Operation. The ſecond and third are daily practiſed, and are called the leſſer, and the great Operation.</p>
               <p>We pretend not to comprehend the two Methods, mentionded by <hi>Proſper Alpinus,</hi> in the fourteenth Chapter, of his 3d. Book of the Medicine of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> where he relates their Practiſe of extracting the Stone of the Bladder, without making Inciſion, but only by Dilatation of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> by blowing into the Yard.</p>
               <p>When I lived in <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſays he, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Arabian</hi> named <hi>Haly,</hi> in great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation for Extracting Stones without Inciſion, took out ſeveral in my preſence from <hi>Horam Bey,</hi> a Turkiſh Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in this manner he ſet about it; he made uſe of a wooden Pipe eight fingers long, and about the thickneſs of ones Thumb; having applied this to the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Yard, he blew into it with great force; at the ſame time with the other hand he preſſed the extremity of the Privy Part towards the <hi>Perineum,</hi> to hinder the Wind from entring into the Bladder; then he ſtopt the mouth of the Pipe, to make the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> ſwell
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59957:49"/>and ſtretch. This being done, a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant put his Finger into the <hi>Anus,</hi> and brought the Stone by little and little to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the neck of the Bladder, and the beginning of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra:</hi> and then the Operator perceiving that the Stone was near the <hi>Perineum,</hi> he ſuddainly and with force drew back the Pipe from the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Yard, and ſo dextrouſly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the Stone, which was about the bigneſs of an Olive-Stone. I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at this Operation which he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon that Turkiſh Commander; and afterwards I ſaw him Practiſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two Jews, one of which was a little Boy, from whom he took 8 ſmall Stones, and the other was grown up, from whom he took one as big as an Olive. This <hi>Arabian</hi> made uſe of the ſame Method to draw Stones out of the Bladder.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Chapter he ſpeaks of a Letter written to him by <hi>Octavius Pove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retus,</hi> a moſt learned Phyſitian in <hi>Egypt,</hi> for the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Months agoe, ſays he, an <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> of <hi>Sidon,</hi> a Chriſtian, Extracted a Stone without Inciſion from another
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59957:50"/>Chriſtian named <hi>Cophtus,</hi> and it was done in this manner. The <hi>Arabian</hi> had many Pipes of different ſizes, much of the ſhape of Flutes, or Pipes which are muſical Inſtruments. They were made of a Cartiliginous matter, which would eaſily ſtreatch: he introduced the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and thruſt it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as far as the Bladder: immediatly thereupon, he blew in it with all his ſtrength to make it ſwell; then he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out that Pipe, and put in a bigger, blowing in it after the ſame manner, and ſo continued charging the Pipes until he put in the fourth, which was the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt; and when he thought by this means that he had dilated the paſſage ſufficiently to make way for the Stone; he placed the Patient in a convenient poſture, and put one Finger into the <hi>Anus,</hi> to bring it towards the neck of the Bladder where the end of that great Pipe was, into which he endeavoured to make the Stone enter. This being done, he put his mouth to the other end of the Pipe, and ſucking with all his ſtrength, he did what he could to draw
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59957:50"/>the Stone towards him, which broke often when it was too big, as it hapned to this Man named <hi>Cophtus;</hi> for he fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him but a part of it, and the reſt being a big and large fragment could not be got out.</p>
               <p>This way, ſaith <hi>Kovoretus,</hi> is eaſie to be learnt, and perhaps a skilful Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion might have better Succeſs in the Practiſe of it, which is a thing to be deſired by thoſe who are troubled with the Stone. <hi>Beverovicius</hi> makes mention of thoſe two ways taken from <hi>Proſper Alpinus.</hi> But it is more pertinent in this place, without examining the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of thoſe two ways, to give the deſcriptions of thoſe which are called the high, the great, and leſſer Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De Franco</hi> was the firſt that practiſed the high Operation, which is ſo called, becauſe it is performed in the <hi>Hypogaſtre,</hi> and though he does not adviſe the doing of it, yet if there were a neceſſity for it, it does not ſeem impracticable in this manner. Let the Patient be laid and held faſt upon a Mattereſs or Quilt, then let
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59957:51"/>a Servant thruſt his fore-finger and midle finger one after another into the <hi>Rectum,</hi> to make the Stone riſe as high as one can; at the ſame time the Operator is to make Inciſion gently above the Groyn and on the ſide of the <hi>Linea-alba</hi> (the white line.) The Bottom of the Bladder may without doubt be opened withoutuhrting the Parts of the lower Belly, becauſe it is ſcituated between the Duplicature of the <hi>Perito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum,</hi> and the fuller that it is of Urine, the more Apparent it will be: by means of the Urine the ſimple Dilatatory may be conducted, and then the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, which after the Dilatory is taken out, may ſerve for a Conductor to the Forceps. Mr. <hi>Jonnot</hi> told me, that Mr. <hi>Bonnet</hi> a Chirurgion who heretofore Practiſed <hi>Lithotomie</hi> in the <hi>Hotel Dieu</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> aſſured him, that he had cut in that manner. Mr. <hi>Petit</hi> a Maſter Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion of that Hoſpital told me that he had ſeen Mr. <hi>Bonnet</hi> Practiſe it upon a young Girl.</p>
               <p>The Cure is to be performed as of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Wounds in the lowor Belly, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways the Method may be changed
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59957:51"/>according as Symptoms happen to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Experience teaches us that the Wounds of the Bladder are not allways Mortal.</p>
               <p>If any one would Practice the High Operation, it would be neceſſary to try many Experiments on dead Bodyes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Water is taken out of the Bladder <hi>De Franco</hi> in the ſame place, Chap. XXXIII. Propoſes another way of cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which is immediately after the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to put in a Tent, unleſs the Stone preſent it ſelf at firſt, and ſome days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when the pain is ceaſed to pull out the Stone. But this way is onely Practiſed when the Operation is Laborious; and inſtead of a Tent, a Pipe is made uſe of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> The Practice of the leſſer Operation for Men.</head>
               <p>THE leſſer Operation hath been ſo called becauſe the Practice thereof requires but a few Inſtuments; it was invented by <hi>Celſus,</hi> and deſcribed in the ſeventh Book, twenty ſixth Chapter,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59957:52"/>as it was heretofore Practiſed; but if the Stone be not towards the neck of the Bladder, and that it be felt in the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum</hi> near to and under the <hi>Scrotum,</hi> the manner of extracting it is different.</p>
               <p>That I may give a clear Notion of the thing, I ſhall here Obſerve what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in many <hi>Lithotomies</hi> in the Year one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty, in the Hoſpital of the Charity of <hi>Paris.</hi> Though I had my ſhare in thoſe Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were Laborious, yet I ſhall onely mention one that happened to <hi>Monſieur Jonnot,</hi> the Circumſtances whereof agreed exactly with other Operations which I performed in his preſence: this Relation will give ground for making two kinds of leſſer Operation for men.</p>
               <p>There was brought to him a Boy of ſeven Years of Age that had been cut the Year before. He needed not make uſe of the <hi>Catheter</hi> to aſſure him of the deſtemper, for with two fingers one might feel the Stone towards the midle of the <hi>Perineum</hi> above the former <hi>Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To hold it faſt, it was needleſs to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59957:52"/>put the fingers into the <hi>Anus,</hi> becauſe the Stone being too high it could not be compreſſed, as is uſually done, when it is in the neck of the Bladder; but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſed the <hi>Scrotum</hi> to be lifted up, and the Skin held ſtrait, <hi>Monſieur Jon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> turning the inſide of the left hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words the Cods, he preſſed the Tumor with his Thumb and fore-finger on both ſides of the Suture where he had obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Stone; at the ſame time he made the Inciſion on the ſide of the Suture upon the Tumor, and having opened a paſſage, with a midle ſized Hook, he extracted the Stone; afterwards feeling with one finger that there were others ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he was obliged to keep the place dilated with the ſame finger that intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Hook, and that the Stone might not ſhift its place, he held it faſt with the fore-finger of the Left-Hand put upon the upper part of the Wound, and with the Thumb on the lower part. By that means he happily finiſhed that Operation, that he might cut the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent by the great Operation; for having pulled out all the ſmall Stones and Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59957:53"/>that were in the <hi>Perineum,</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced by the Yard a furrowed <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> werewith he found another Stone in the Bladder, and upon that <hi>Catheter</hi> he continued the Inciſion with the other Circumſtances whereof we ſhall ſpeak in the great Operation. I was neceſſitated to do the ſame to a young Man of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two Years of Age.</p>
               <p>I remember that before Monſieur <hi>Jonnot</hi> made uſe of the <hi>Catheter</hi> to cut him by the great Operation, be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the Yard a great ſtreight Wire or <hi>Stilet</hi> to force down ſome Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that ſtuck a little higher than the Inciſion, whilſt he compreſſed the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra</hi> underneath, and then putting his Thumb below the Wound, he drew them out with a ſmal Scoop without any trouble.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 81</p>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 81</p>
               </figure>
               <p>It is not needful to make the Patient jump before he be cut by the leſſer Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; if he be a little Boy, and the Stone in the Neck of the Bladder, it is enough, after that he is put into a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and held faſt by the Servants, that the Chirurgion dip his fore-finger and middle-finger into Oyl, the nails being pared; and if one Finger be not ſuffii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, that he thruſt them one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Fundament, as far as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he can, that they may reach beyond the Stone, and preſs it down to the Neck of the Bladder, betwixt the <hi>Rectum</hi> and the <hi>Os Pubis,</hi> a Servant in the mean time lifting up the <hi>Scrotum</hi> with one hand, and with the other armed with a Compreſs leaning upon the Belly, to make the Stone come down; then the Chirurgion is to dry the <hi>Perineum,</hi> and ſtretch the Skin very ſtrait with his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fingers, as it is repreſented in this Figure.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59957:56"/>
               <p>The Tumor that the Stone covered with Teguments makes, renders the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the ſide of the Suture, which may be made long enough for extracting of the Stone; care neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs muſt be had, to avoid the <hi>Rectum,</hi> the <hi>Hemmorhoid</hi> Veins and the Cods. One muſt not fear the ſpoyling of the edge or point of the <hi>Biſtori,</hi> for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time that it is to be uſed of new, it muſt be ſet again.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as the Inciſion is made, the Stone appears, and then the Operator lays aſide the <hi>Biſtori,</hi> and takes the Hook or <hi>Crochet;</hi> he is to hide it in his Hand as much as he can, the end of its Handle being towards the little Finger, and the fore-Finger covering the length of its Body: without drawing the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers out of the <hi>Rectum,</hi> the Hook is to be ſlipt in betwixt the <hi>Pubis,</hi> and the Stone in this manner.</p>
               <p>When the Hook is behind the Stone, and that the Operator intends to pluck it out, the Handle of it ought to be in the Hand with the end reſting upon the Thumb, that it may be uſed with greater</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 82</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:57"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:57"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 83</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59957:58"/>
               <p>The Fingers are not to be taken out of the <hi>Anus</hi> before the extraction, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs when the Stone breaks becauſe of its ſoftneſs or ſhape which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times crooked like a Creſſant, if the reſt cannot be extracted with the Hook or a little Forceps, the next courſe is, to remove the Fingers out of the <hi>Anus,</hi> and introduce the Button into the wound for ſearching of the Stone, and having felt it, conduct a Forceps upon the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton to lay hold of it, and gently draw it out.</p>
               <p>By what Operation ſoever an Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor may cut, when the Stone breaks, though many Stones have been taken out, it is ſtill neceſſary to introduce the Button to ſearch and examine if there be no more fragments remaining.</p>
               <p>When thoſe that are of Age and grown up, are cut by the leſſer Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is not neceſſary to make the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion ſo high as in the great Operation, becauſe one cuts exactly upon the Stone, and it is alſo eaſier to avoid hurting of the <hi>Rectum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Patient hath been already cut;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59957:59"/>the Inciſion is to be made upon the <hi>Cicatrice</hi> or the <hi>Fiſtula.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> The manner of both the leſſer and greater Operation for Women.</head>
               <p>WOmen and Maids are cut by the leſſer Operation, introducing the fore-finger and middle-finger into the <hi>Vagina <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>teri,</hi> if it can be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Violence, or into the <hi>Rectum,</hi> for feeling of the Stone, and holding it firm, whilſt with the other hand the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor preſſes the lower Belly to make the Stone come down. Then he is to make uſe of the hollow ſtreight <hi>Catheter,</hi> which being introduced into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> is to be held by a Servant, and the <hi>Orifice</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> is to be dilated by a ſimple Dilatatory, conducted in the <hi>Cavitie</hi> of the <hi>Catheter:</hi> it is not to be dilated too far forward, becauſe the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is ſhort, and that the dilaacerted <hi>Fibres</hi> may not hinder the unvoluntary
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59957:59"/>emiſſion of the Urine, the dilatation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, the <hi>Catheter</hi> is taken out with the Dilatatory, and the Fingers being ſtill in the ſame place into which they were introduced, the Stone is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out with the Hook or a Forceps, in the ſame manner as from little Boys.</p>
               <p>Women and Girles may be excuſed from the violence which they ſuſſex by the leſſer Operation, becauſe the great Operation is more convenient for the better ſucceeding in it, the Patient is to be placed upon the Chair, or upon the end of a Mattereſs, and that Conductor which is ſhaped like a Sword, and hath a bill, is to be introduced into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra,</hi> then a ſmall ſimple Dilatatory; and having made a moderate dilatation, whilſt the Dilatatory is ſtill open, the Chirurgion according to his own diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the bigneſs of the Stone, may cut a little ſideways to the right and left, the external Orifice of the Paſſage, then draw out the Dilatatory, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Forceps along the Conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to take hold of the Stone, and to extract it in the uſual manner, its ſcarce
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59957:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:59957:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:59957:61"/>credible how much the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> may be dilated both in Men and Women.</p>
               <p>There are ſome Operators who having introduced the ſtreight hollow <hi>Catheter,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thruſt in one of the Conductors, ſhaped like a Sword that hath a bill; and the <hi>Catheter</hi> being drawn out, they ſlip eaſily in the other Conductor, which is ſorked, becauſe the firſt has a line that directs the ſecond. Between thoſe two Conductors which they preſs betwixt the Fore-finger and Middle-finger of the left Hand; they thruſt in a Forceps to continue the Operation. Others ſuccesfully make uſe of a narrow <hi>Gorgeret</hi> which ſerves for a Conductor to the Forceps. Mr. <hi>Jonnot</hi> makes only uſe of a hollow ſtreight <hi>Catheter,</hi> or of a large <hi>Probe</hi> or <hi>Stilet</hi> for conducting the Forceps.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:59957:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the Practice of the great Operation for Men, and of circumſtances during the time of the Operation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JOannes de Romanis</hi> a Phyſician of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona,</hi> in the year 1520. Invented and Practiſed at <hi>Rome,</hi> the great Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo called, becauſe it requires more Inſtruments than other Methodes do.</p>
               <p>Men who are cut by the great Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration occaſion more trouble, not only in reſpect of the Operation, but likewiſe in reſpect of the Cure; becauſe their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> is crooked, long and narrow, and their way of living renders that Part many times ſubject to more Diſeaſes than thoſe Parts in Women.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 89</p>
               </figure>
               <p>This poſture is ſomewhat terrible to the Patient, and therefore ſince there are ſome Men of a ſtrong Reſolution and invincible Courage, if they be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſuffer theſe <hi>Ligatures;</hi> it will be ſufficient to bind their Thighs and Legs in the manner deſcribed, and cauſe their Arms to be held by two Men; or perhaps they may like it better to have their hands tied a part by themſelves, making them lay their wriſts one upon another which being tied together by the midle of a Bandage wrapped two or three times about them and two indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent hard Knots, the two ends are to be brought about the the neck and tied, together with a running knot, ſo that the hands reſt about the pit of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach or the <hi>Cartilago Enſiformis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſaw a Genteleman who had had his Leg cut off, cut at Mr. <hi>Jonnots.</hi> his Arme was tied on the ſame ſide with his Thighs and the want of his Leg was ſupplied by the number of Servants who held
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59957:64"/>him faſt if one or both his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> had been cut off, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the number of Men who could have held him by the Arms and Stumps, whilſt others leaned upon his Shoulders, without any uſe of Ligarures.</p>
               <p>Women ought to be Situated in the ſame poſture.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Scarffes are applying, it is fit that the Chrurgion ſhould ſpeak to the Patient, but in few words, that he look upon him and encourage him with diſcourſe, ſhuning every thing that is undecent, becauſe one muſt be very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, to oblige thoſe that are preſent to be ſilent and with reſpect to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, which wonderfully comforts a Patient; calling to mind, that to laugh at the diſeaſe, the infirmity, or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a Patient, is to inſult over a man in affluction. <hi>Neminem riſeris ne miſerum ririſeris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were better to have but a few ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators, becauſe a great many may incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode the Operator, frighten the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and put a bad conſtruction on the accidents that ſometimes accompany the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59957:65"/>Operation: it is fit, as much as conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently may be, that a Church-man ſhould be preſent to talke now and then to the Patient, that may help to divert his pain, and encreaſe his Patience dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Operation.</p>
               <p>When the Patient is ſeated, the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, is to place his People to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him and make him ſpread open his knees, lean upon his ſhoulders, and to lift up the <hi>Scrotum</hi> or hold the <hi>Catheter,</hi> if a Servant preſent a Biſtori, he is to be on the right ſide of the Operator, who is to cut with the right hand; and he ſhall hold it in this faſhion.</p>
               <p>With the Right-hand in which he hides the Blade of the Biſtori. The Operator when he takes it, is to put his hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the handle, the other Servants are placed in the ſame manner for the leſſer, as for the great Operation; but they hold the Patient in a different manner, as it hath been repreſented by the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of surgical instrument</figDesc>
                  <p>page 92</p>
               </figure>
               <p>Before the Operation there is ſometimes a <hi>Procidentia</hi> or falling of the <hi>Anus</hi> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the ſtraining of the Patient: if the falling be conſiderable, the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor may endeavour to thruſt it up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violence, and then lay a Bolſter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Anus,</hi> which a Servant is to preſs hard: but if the Servants hand hinder the Operator, there is nothing to be put upon the <hi>Rectum;</hi> for after the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is over it is reduced, and many times returns again of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>if the Patient have been cut already, the Inciſion is to be made upon the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrice, or the fiſtula, as hath been ſaid ſpeaking of the leſſer Operation one may cut on the Right ſide as well as on the Left, taking heed not to cut the ſuture, becauſe it does not ſo eaſily cicatrice, and is alſo attended by many accidents.</p>
               <p>The Inciſion in Children is made at leaſt two fingers breadth in length; in men 3 or four fingers breadth or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, according as the Stone is thought
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59957:67"/>to be of bigneſs, and according to the Groſneſs of the Subject. Not that it ought to be made too large, for when the Stone is in the paſſage, if the Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be too ſmall, recourſe may be had to a Cut with the Biſtori, or with a pair of Cizars in a convenient place. The Inciſion of the Skin and Membrances is eaſily made, but many times the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra</hi> is not ſufficiently opened unleſs one preſs the Biſtori hard in the furrow of the Staff; Inciſion is never made in the neck of the Bladder, but always in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and experience convinces that a great Inciſion in that Operation is as ſoon cicatriced as a ſmall one.</p>
               <p>The Patient being ſet in a poſture and bound with the Scarffes, his Arms and Legs are held by two ſtrong Men, and, if need be, two others take care to keep his knees aſunder, a Servant gets up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Chair to preſs upon his ſhouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, during the time of the Operation, which is performed, if it be poſſible, by the leſſer Operation, or at leaſt in the great (which is commonly made uſe for Men and litttle boys) by introducing a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59957:67"/>furrowed <hi>Catheter,</hi> wherewith the Oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator ſearches, and is certain if there be a Stone or not.</p>
               <p>If nothing be felt with the furrowed <hi>Catheter,</hi> it is neceſſary to introduce a <hi>Catheter,</hi> whoſe bill is not ſo long, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Patient void his Urine; and if there be a Stone it will by that means be more eaſily found, becauſe when it Floats, being little and ſmooth, it will follow the courſe of the Urine; and the <hi>Catheter</hi> will turn better in the Bladder. When the Stone is found the furrrowed <hi>Catheter</hi> is again to be introduced.</p>
               <p>If the Patient hath been cut, it is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to introduce the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one is to be taken of a ſize that would ſuit with a younger Subject, and ſufficiently long, according to the age of him that is to be ſearched.</p>
               <p>There are ſome Operators who hold the <hi>Catheter</hi> themſelves when they make the Inciſion: others cauſe a Servant to hold it, who is placed at the ſide of the Chair, oppoſit to the Groyn whereon the Operator is to make the Inciſion; for example, the Chirurgion performing his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59957:68"/>Operation on the left ſide of the ſuture, the Servant ſhall be on the Patients Right-hand, and having wiped and dried the <hi>Scrotum</hi> and <hi>Perineum,</hi> he ſhall lift up the Cods with the Left-hand, and ſhall reſt his other hand upon the Rings and end of the the <hi>Catheter,</hi> inclining the furrowing a little towards the Patients left ſide, and he muſt take care not to make it come out of the Bladder, which he may avoid: if he bring not the Rings of the <hi>Catheter</hi> too near the Belly. The Chirurgion ought to mind firſt bidding him hold faſt and not waver, and cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others to lean upon the Patients ſhoulders, becauſe at that very time the Operator ought to pull the ſuture to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the right ſide, placing the Thumb of his Left-hand near the <hi>Anus,</hi> and his other fingers near the <hi>Scrotum</hi> having felt with the fore finger of the Right-hand, and obſerved the place where the back of the <hi>Catheter</hi> is in the ſame manner as one does to find the Vein before blood letting) pulling ſtill the ſuture to the Right, with the Right-hand he is to take the Biſtori mounted, which the Servant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59957:68"/>in the place deſigned, as you ſee repreſented by this Figure.</p>
               <p>In making inciſion he is to ſearch for the furrowing of the <hi>Catheter,</hi> into which he is to thruſt the point of the <hi>Biſtory,</hi> he is to preſs hard, ſwathing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove towards the Cods, and below ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wriſt, that the point of the <hi>Biſtory</hi> may be always directed into the furrowing underneath the <hi>Catheter</hi> that the Urethra may be exactly cut, avoiding the Scrotum, the Rectum and the Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoide veins; then he ſhall return back the <hi>Biſtory.</hi> And take the Gorgeret to introduce it into the furrowing; after that with the left hand he ſhall lay hold on the <hi>Catheter</hi> by the end which the Servant held.</p>
               <p>To prevent the Fingers of the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors left hand from ſliding during the time of the Inciſion, he may make uſe of a very narrow compreſs, to help him to preſſe and pull the ſuture towards the patients right ſide.</p>
               <p>If in making Inciſion the Operator himſelf hold the <hi>Catheter,</hi> the Servant who extends the <hi>Perineum</hi> may upon the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59957:69"/>ſame account put very narrow Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſſes betwixt his Fingers and the Skin, that ſo he may hold the two ſides of the ſuture firmer towards the Thighs; by that means the Humidity will not hinder him to preſs upon them as much as is neceſſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Ruffin</hi> a ſworn Chirurgeon of <hi>Paris,</hi> one of the ableſt of his time, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Operation in this manner in the Hoſpital of the <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 99</p>
               </figure>
               <p>The furrowing of the <hi>Catheter</hi> being diſcovered and the <hi>Biſtory</hi> returned back, he took a Conductor with an elbow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the middle which is compoſed of two in the form of a Sword, he thruſt the Bill of it into the furrowing ſtill holding the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and when it was introduced into the Bladder, he drew out the <hi>Catheter,</hi> and conveighed his <hi>Forceps</hi> betwixt the Branches of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor to introduce it into the Bladder:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59957:71"/>the Conductor being taken out he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the Operation.</p>
               <p>Theſe two ways are very good, and have both their advantages, becauſe when the Operator himſelf holds the <hi>Catheter</hi> he is ſure what place it is in; but alſo after the Inciſion, ſometimes it is hard to find the furrowing becauſe of Fat, Membrans and Blood that hide it; it is true that after Inciſion the point of the <hi>Biſtory</hi> may be left in the furrowing, and may be held by ſome body whilſt the Chirurgeon ſlides the Bill of the Gorgeret along the <hi>Biſtory,</hi> but when a Servant holds the <hi>Catheter,</hi> after that the Inciſion is made and that the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator hath given back the <hi>Biſtory,</hi> as we have Juſt now deſcribed, he may put the Nail of his left Thumb into the Wound, and having found the ſlit or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing, thruſt therein the Gorgeret which ought to be hid in his right hand, ſo that the right fore-finger cover the length of it, ſuffering nothing almoſt to appear but the Bill: So ſoon as the Bill is in the furrowing, he takes the <hi>Catheter</hi> by the rings in the left hand, as is here repreſented.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 100</p>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:72"/>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:59957:72"/>
               <p>And now there is great care to be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in introducing the Gorgeret into the Bladder, for if the Patient puſh hard he may make the <hi>Catheter</hi> to come out, and then bad accidents happen; for if one thruſt forwards the Gorgeret and then the <hi>Forceps,</hi> when they are not in the Bladder, a ſpace is made betwixt the Urethra and the Rectum. To avoid miſtakes the Operator ought to have an attentive mind, and not talk. And then having paſſed the Bill of the Conductor called the Gorgeret into the furrowing of the Catheter, he is to hold them faſt, keeping the Bill always in; And as if one intended by guiding and making it ſlide along and under the furrowing, to thruſt the Bill upwards; by this means one is ſure to introduce it into the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and holding it with his right hand the Catheter muſt be diſengaged from the Gorgeret by turning it with the left, and then ſoftly and eaſily drawn out of the Yard. A certain ſign that the Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret is in the Bladder, is the emiſſion of Urine along the Conductor; that is, if there be any in the Bladder.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59957:73"/>
               <p>When the Gorgeret is in the Bladder, and the Catheter drawn out, it is taken hold of with the left hand, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>Forceps</hi> with the right, which is to be thruſt upon and along the ſame Gorgeret in this manner.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 103</p>
               </figure>
               <p>The Button being blunt hurts not the parts in paſſing, and when it is in the Bladder (which may be known, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it may be eaſily turned every way) the Stone is ſoftly to be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for by gently jogging and moving the Inſtrument; which being felt, the Chirurgeon is to take the Button in the left hand, conducting with the right the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59957:75"/>
                  <hi>Forceps</hi> cloſe upon the Button into the Bladder, this is the Figure of it.</p>
               <p>If it be a crooked <hi>Forceps,</hi> whilſt it is introducing, the Bill being turned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Yard, the rings are more to be raiſed, as may be obſerved in this laſt Figure, in a manner different from the former Figure, Page 92. which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the ſtreight <hi>Forceps</hi> conducted upon the Gorgeret with the right hand bending lower upon the left. The Crooked <hi>Forceps</hi> is made uſe of, when the Stone is thought to be very near to the Groyn; but moſt commonly the ſtreight <hi>Forcipes</hi> are ſufficient, and both the one and the other ought to be laid upon the line of the Button, ſo that it touch on both ſides.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 104</p>
               </figure>
               <p>It is to be obſerved that as often as one would change a <hi>Forceps,</hi> or introduce it, there is a neceſſity of making uſe of the Button, except immediately after the Inciſion is made, when the Conductor is introduced, on which the <hi>Forceps</hi> is thruſt forwards.</p>
               <p>Remember that after the Inciſion is made, and the Conductor introduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the furrowing, when one would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engage the Catheter, or that it is out of the Yard, the Patient ſometimes ſtrugles before the Conductor be in the Bladder; or other ways when the Ure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra has not been cut enough towards the Bladder, or that the Bill of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor be not dextrouſly thruſt into the Slit or Furrowing, inſtead of entering into the Bladder, a ſpace is made betwixt it and the Rectum. Then muſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor be drawn back; and if afterwards one cannot introduce the Button, it will
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59957:77"/>be neceſſary to take the ſame furrowed Catheter, or one ſomewhat ſmaller and leſs Furrowed: For better paſſing it into the Bladder, making uſe of the Second way of ſearching Men, deſcribed in the Ninth Chap. by that means the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is gently introduced into the Urethra, without turning of it any way, leſt it ſhould come out at the Inciſion, and when it is paſſed into the Bladder, the furrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to be ſearched by the Wound with the Bill of the Gorgeret, that ſo the Operation may be continued.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 106</p>
               </figure>
               <p>There is as little uſe of this made as can conveniently be, nevertheleſs if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity require it is uſed; after which it is pulled out, and without parting from the Gorgeret, the Operator takes a cloſe <hi>Forceps</hi> conducting it into the Bladder to ſearch for the Stone, where it muſt be gently turned and jogged every way, as hath been ſaid.</p>
               <p>It is to be minded alſo that it hath been ſaid, that ſo ſoon as the <hi>Forceps</hi> is in the Bladder, it may be moderately opened with both hands to dilate the paſſage a little, and at the ſame time to bring the Rings almoſt together, and afterwards with one hand it may be thruſt and moved gently to the right and left, up and down where the Sphincter of the Rectum is, to feel the Stone, ſometimes turning the <hi>Forceps</hi> ſo that one of its Rings be higher than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thereby endeavouring to lay hold of the Stone, which may be flat, or lye hid at one ſide of the Bladder.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:59957:79"/>
               <p>When it is found, the <hi>Forceps</hi> is to be opened with both hands, to gripe what has been felt. The Operator is ſometimes ſo fortunate as to take good hold of the Stone in a ſmall time; which is to be known, becauſe after that the <hi>Forceps</hi> hath been opened, the Rings cannot be made to meet again, and ſome hard matter is to be felt betwixt the Teeth: This is the ſureſt ſign, for very ſmall Stones may be taken hold of about the middle of the <hi>Forcipes,</hi> where they are more bent than elſe where; which will not hinder but that the Rings may be brought to meet; but ſtill ſome hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is to be felt. This hath happened to me, and it was thought that there had been nothing; but I felt that hardneſs in the <hi>Forceps,</hi> and I have the Stone of that Operation ſtill by me.</p>
               <p>When the Stone is laid hold of, one muſt not at firſt pull towards him, but it is requiſite to turn gently the <hi>Forceps</hi> to the right and left, holding it with one or both hands according to the convenience of the Operator, that ſo he may know if the Stone lye right in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59957:79"/>the Teeth, and diſintangle it from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Plicatures, pulling to him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards without violence: the Rings of the <hi>Forceps</hi> are to be raiſed and low'rd alternatly, to make the Stone ſlide with greater eaſe. If one have made uſe of a crooked <hi>Forceps,</hi> the Bill of it muſt have been turned towards the Pubis juſt at the paſſage of bringing it out; and the Rings be very near the Yard: that one may not be miſtaken, it would be neceſſary to put a mark upon one of the Rings of the <hi>Forceps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Stone is in the <hi>Forceps,</hi> ſpecial care is to be had not to turn it quite round, becauſe if the Stone be big or uneven, it will much confuſe the parts of the Bladder: If the Stone be ſoft, it breaks and moulders, and the <hi>Forceps</hi> eaſily ſhuts; but then one feels as it were a heap of ſand, and then the Rings are not to be brought wholly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, becauſe then a ſmall matter of gravel would be drawn out, and the parts of the Bladder might be hurt; the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps</hi> with what is betwixt the Teeth of it is to be pulled out, and this is to be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59957:80"/>reiterated conducting it upon the Button, as often as ſhall be judged neceſſary: And then a Tent or Pipe is to be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, as ſhall be mentioned in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapter.</p>
               <p>When the Operator judges the Stone to be flat and of the ſhape of an Almond, he may endeavour to make one of the Teeth of the <hi>Forcipes</hi> ſlide under, and the other above; though commonly the Stones are taken ſideways, and when it is taken hold of, he is to turn the <hi>Forceps</hi> again, ſo that the thickneſs of the Stone may anſwer to the length of the Inciſion.</p>
               <p>Sometimes a Stone of the ſhape of a large Hens-Egg is caught hold of by its two ends: which may be gueſſed by the great diſtance that is obſerved betwixt the Rings of the <hi>Forceps,</hi> nay one may ſee it when the Stone is near the paſſage; to keep it faſt, the <hi>Forceps</hi> is to be thruſt back into the Bladder, the Teeth of it a little opened that the Stone may be looſe, and it will turn without fail; by that means it is afterward taken hold of by its thickneſs ſideways, and the paſſage thereby leſs dilated.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:59957:80"/>
               <p>If the Stone be adherent and ſtick ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloſe, it were better to delay the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of it, becauſe ſuppuration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the ſeparation thereof. And if the Operator cannot hold the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps</hi> faſt enough, he may make uſe of a Napkin to wrap the Rings in, that his hands may not ſlip.</p>
               <p>When it is exceſſively big, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to let it alone than to expoſe the Patient to evident Death, eſpecially if Age and other circumſtances are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Operation. <hi>Pareus</hi> and <hi>Bevero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicius</hi> adviſe to break it with <hi>Forcipes</hi> whoſe Teeth reſemble the Teeth of a great Saw: And <hi>Tevenin,</hi> Chap. 121. Of his Operations, propoſes the introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of a pretty long Tent or Pipe, to hinder that the Stone fall not upon the Sphincter, that ſo the Patient may make his water; that Pipe ſhould ſhut with a Screw, that it may be uſed as need requires.</p>
               <p>When all the Stones have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in an Operation, it is not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to introduce a Tent or Pipe: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs there are ſome Operators who
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59957:81"/>always uſe them, to void, as they ſay, the clots of congealed Blood; but they liquifie and come out by the Yard, or by the wound without a Tent which hinders the reuniting of the divided parts that ſtill are Bleeding. It is true that they who well underſtand the conduct of that Operation may ſucceed in it, without leaving a Tent or Pipe long in the place; but yet it is ſometimes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to uſe it for ſome days when there is an Ulcer in the Bladder; that injections may be the more convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made into it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> What time the Patient may be kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Operation, and what is to be done, when it is hard and laborious.</head>
               <p>AN Operation is called hard and laborious, when by a skilful man it is not performed in a ſhort time. In ſuch a caſe the Patient is not to be held in pain until the Stone or all its parts be extracted. Sometimes it ſo ſtops the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59957:81"/>paſſage, that the Conductor or <hi>Forceps</hi> cannot but with great difficulty enter: and therefore an expert Chirurgeon will not ſcruple to take out his Inſtruments, and with his Finger or the Button thruſt back the Stone into the Bladder; and will afterwards make uſe of the Botton and <hi>Forceps</hi> to continue the Operation.</p>
               <p>It many times happens that after that the Stone hath been often laid hold of, it eſcapes and mounts up again, becauſe the <hi>Forceps</hi> gives way, or the Teeth of it are not good, or otherways becauſe the Stone is monſtrous in reſpect of the paſſage, or that it breaks when it is held too ſtrait, or becauſe it is ſoft, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be extracted when it adheres.</p>
               <p>Theſe circumſtances are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved very exactly, and the Chirurgeon ought not to be more careful in his Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, than in conſidering the ſtrength and Age of the Patient, with the time that he has been upon the Chair, keeping him under the Operation rather too ſhort a time than too long, leſt he be ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by death, if he be made to endure too much: But if after the Operation hath
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59957:82"/>been methodically carried on, nothing is extracted becauſe there was no Stone in the Bladder, or that the Stone is ſmall, or if fragments remained, he may take the Button with a ſcoop by the ſmall or middle; and introduce the ſcoop or ſpoon into the wound, and ſo endeavour to extract ſomewhat, and this having been two or three times reiterated, he ought to make uſe of a Tent or Pipe proportionable to the ſubject, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to Art. For introducing it he may make uſe, if he pleaſes, and with more ſecurity of the Button, put into the Inciſion, and having dipped the end of the Tent in Oyl, he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct it along the Button even to the Bladder, in this manner.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of stone removal procedure</figDesc>
                  <p>page 114</p>
               </figure>
               <p>When the fragments are but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately big, they may be extracted a Bed, and it is good to leave the Tent until one be certain that there is nothing more remaining within: which may be known, if one obſerve what came out during the Operation, or afterwards with the Medicines.</p>
               <p>Moreover, after the Tent is taken out, one may introduce a Catheter crooked at the end, or a big Wire through the cavity of the Tent, without taking it out; and by ſeveral little joggs or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſearch as far up as can be done without Pain. One may likewiſe make uſe of a Feather to clear the Tent of Blood, or of Slime and Purulent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59957:84"/>that are formed in the Bladder. The injection of warm Barley Water is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and after the firſt day one may gently preſs the Belly with the hand in time of Dreſſing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of the Symptoms of <hi>Lithotomy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Symptoms of <hi>Lithotomy</hi> are divided into thoſe which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Operation, and thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, the firſt called Concomitant and the others Subſequent.</p>
               <p>Accidents which accompany the Operation are Hemorrhage or Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the length of time which makes it to be called Laborious, the Bruiſing and Breaking of the Stone, the difficulty of extracting it, or the impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, the number and fragments which cannot be extracted becauſe of their big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, numerouſneſs, or weakneſs of the Patient: ſometimes alſo nothing is found, though the Patient hath been ſearched and examined before. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſion Superveens if the <hi>Forceps</hi> be thruſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59957:84"/>too rudely or too frequently when it is in the Bladder, Excoriation, or even a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Bladder, or other parts as well by the bigneſs and aſperties of the Stone, as by the Teeth of the <hi>Forcipes,</hi> if they be ſhut cloſe when they are in the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becauſe it is wrinkled, and the ſides of its Body or Bottom may be laid hold on without the Stone or with it.</p>
               <p>The Symptoms that follow the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Cure by <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> are a painful tenſion of the Belly, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Urine, Watchings, Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the parts affected, Looſeneſs, Diarrhaea, Worms, Ecchymoſes, Fluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Abſceſſes, Excoriations, Itchings and Putrifaction, Ulcers in the <hi>Scrotum,</hi> and the Neighbouring parts, Ulcers and Putrifaction of the parts of the Bladder, to great, or too long Suppurations; voiding of Purulent matter by the wound, or with the Urine by the Yard, Feavers, univerſal or particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions or Maraſmus's, Hemorrhages as in the time of Operation, Syncope's Convulſions, Vomitings, Lightheaded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Deliriums and Shiverings.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:59957:85"/>
               <p>The painful tenſion of the Belly is cauſed by an inflammation that attracts a Fluxion, becauſe the Ligaments which ſuſpend the Bladder, and the other parts to which it adheres, have ſuffered violence: The Feaver and Reſtleſneſs proceed from the <hi>Intemperies</hi> of the chief parts, agitated by the paſſions of the mind; And the Hemorrhage from the Inciſion, or Eroſion of the Veſſels: The retention of Urine is occaſioned by coagulated Blood, or the inflamation of the parts during ſuppuration, or by ſome little Stone fallen down from the Kidneys, or a fragment remaining after the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: The inflammation comes from a circulat motion of the Humours; the Scourings, looſeneſs of the Belly, and Worms in Children through the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Phlegme; the <hi>Ecchimaſis</hi> is an effect of extravaſated Blood; the Abſceſs is produced by a collection and continuance of Humours in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the parts: the too great and too long ſuppuration, by the quantity of the matter whereof the Abſceſs is form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or by the Ulcerated Kidneys, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59957:85"/>by the liquefaction of the Humors of the whole Body, of which part do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purate whilſt the reſt are diſperſed by Tranſpiration or Looſeneſs, which cauſes at the ſame time a Maraſmus or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation of the whole Body: The Ulcer of the Bladder is cauſed by contuſion and ſuppuration of its parts, which excites the running of Purulent matter by the Yard or Wound: Fungous carnoſities by a ſuperfluity of ill concocted and too ſerous Blood; the Itching and excori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation are the effects of the ſharpneſs of Urine, or of too ſtrait bandage; the Putrifaction of the Ulcer comes from the corruption of the Humors and of the Air, or from the too great humidity of Medicines, and the Virulence, from the Acrimony of the Humors and Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The Vomiting happens after the Operation, becauſe many nervous Fibres of the ſixth pair are diſtributed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the Ventricle. There are other accidents occaſioned by the diſtribution of the Nerves, which paſs through the holes of the <hi>Os ſacrum</hi> common to the Sphincters of the Bladder and <hi>Anus,</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:59957:86"/>which have been bruiſed or lacerated by the <hi>Forcipes,</hi> or by the aſperities of a great Stone, eſpecially when the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath been hard and laborious.</p>
               <p>The Fainting or Syncope, is occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by a great Flux of Blood, and the diſſipation of the Spirits: The Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on happens by Vomitings, the Diarrhea &amp; Hemorrhage, which hinder the Nerves from receiving a ſufficient quantity of Spirits: The Delirium and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headedneſs Superveens, when there has been ſo great a diſſipation of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits, that the Brain retains not enough for it ſelf, and for ſupplying the whole Body with a quantity ſufficient for performing the functions of its ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts. In a word, Fate puts and end to all theſe accidents by deſtroying the Machine; that is to ſay, by aboliſhing of Motion at the inſtant when the Soul is ſeparated from the Body.</p>
               <p>If any be ſurprized that we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken nothing of Pain, they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that that is a Symptome, or rather an eſſential property of all diſeaſes of the parts that are capable of feeling,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59957:86"/>ſince it always happens, where there is an <hi>Intemperies</hi> with a ſolution of continuity of the ſoft parts and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence it is more ſenſible in <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> than all the other accidents that we have been ſpeaking of.</p>
               <p>Theſe Symptoms have their cauſes, their Diagnoſtick and Prognoſtick ſigns: ſome are the cauſe and the ſigns of others, and all the Symptoms in general, are cauſed by Pain, Fear, Hemorrhage, Contuſion and Dilaceration of the parts.</p>
               <p>The Prognoſticks are taken from the time, the violence, and the ſtate of the ſubject in which the accidents happen. The Symptoms that appear at firſt, are not ſo dangerous, and thoſe which laſt long, or happen in a Cacochymick Body, are more to be feared.</p>
               <p>An Operator who is expert in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Operation will avoid many conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant Symptoms. There are ſome nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleblades who have the knack of feigning that they have extracted a Stone, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey one, though they have found none.</p>
               <p>The Symptoms that follow the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, are either by themſelves apart,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59957:87"/>or many together according to their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, corrected by various Medicins.</p>
               <p>The firſt care is to aſſwage Pain by Imbrocations and Fomentations: a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhageis ſometimes to be feared, and therefore aſtringent topicks are to be employed for preſerving the treaſure of life. The loſs of Blood ceaſes common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the weakneſs of the Patient, becauſe the Medicins that are applied to this part are diſſolved by the Urine; and beſides no other bandage but the contentive can be uſed, when in other parts one may put his Finger upon the Orifice or opening of the Veſſel, or cut it in two, apply to it a Button, a Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Pledgets and Compreſſes. It is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obſerved that the firſt dreſſing be kept on, for the ſpace of Twenty four Hours at moſt: it is tenderly to be taken off, leaving a Pledget upon the place out of which the Blood does Iſſue, if it can be known; and if the Hemorrhage recurr, recourſe is had to aſtringents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:59957:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of the Method of curing thoſe that are Cut, and removing their Symptoms.</head>
               <p>WE come inſenſibly to the cure by <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> the method of which is either general or particular. Having ſpoken of the Cauſes, Kinds, Signs and Prognoſticks of the Symptoms, it is now proper to give you a notion of thoſe things which ought to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the time of the Operation until the perfect cure of the Patient. By that means we may treat in particular of the remedies againſt accident; ſince they happen whilſt the Patient is in the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons hands.</p>
               <p>By the general cure by <hi>Lithotomy</hi> we underſtand that wherein no Symptoms happen which are of the Nature of a cauſe. And by the particular cure, that which is attended by troubleſome accidents, ſuch as cauſe the methods to be changed: of each of theſe we ſhall ſpeak apart.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59957:88"/>Suppoſing that the Chirurgeon hath ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully performed his Operation, he muſt dreſs the Wound, and endeavour by the help of Medicines to cure it.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing that is to be obſerved after the Operation, whilſt he that is cut is ſtill in poſture, and that with all expedition he is a clearing of the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if any have been uſed, is to put upon the Inciſion a ſquare dry Compreſs about three or four Fingers breadth in bigneſs and indifferently thick, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on with one hand, to take the Patient about the Body, and with aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and help to carry him to Bed.</p>
               <p>We have already ſaid that the Collar may be put on before the Operation, afterwards taking a Frond or Truſs ſuitable to the Patient, it is to be laid upon his Back above the Buttocks, that ſo the two heads or ſtraps called the twins, and which may be then called the ſuperiour, may ſerve for a Girdle, the Body or middle of the bandage, in the mean time, declining towards the place where the Inciſion hath been made, which hinders the ſtopping up of the <hi>Anus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:59957:88"/>
               <p>Before the two ſuperiour ſtraps of the Frond or Truſs he tied together for making of a Girdle, Imbrocation is to be made upon the Belly and the Cods with the warm Oyl of Roſes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, to prevent the painful tenſion of the Body, and to cure it, and an Aſtringent Plaſter is to be applied to the Belly, with the <hi>Ventriere</hi> or Belly peice ſoaked in warm Oxycrat; then muſt the two ſuperiour or upper ſtraps of the Truſs be tied together to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Patients right ſide, the one of them paſſing under the Collar.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, the Compreſs which was put upon the Wound dry, and is ſince the Operation ſteeped in Blood, is to be taken off, and Medicines applied to the place.</p>
               <p>If there be a Hemorrhage Aſtringent, Powders and Pledgets are to be made uſe of; and when there is no Hemorrhage, an indifferent thick Pledget covered with Aſtringent is to be put upon the Wound with a Triangular Plaſter cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Aſtringent, and the Cods are to be kept up with a Truſs whoſe ends paſs
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59957:89"/>along the two Groins, and afterward a ſmall Square Compreſs dipped in warm Oxycrat, as the Truſs ought to be, is to be put upon the Plaſter holding all the dreſſing of the Wound with one hand (for one muſt be ambidexter) and with the other hand taking hold of the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage betwixt the Thighs, by the end which is near the <hi>Anus,</hi> it is to be brought over the little ſquare Compreſs that is upon the Wound, and carried along the left Groin; declining be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Thigh and the Hand that holdeth on the dreſſing, and that end is to be left upon the Girdle ſtill holding the dreſſing faſt: then one muſt take the other end which is more remote from the <hi>Anus,</hi> and giving it a turn outwards towards the Body of the bandage to make an equal compreſſure, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to paſs over the Square Compreſs that is upon the Wound, and diſenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Fingers wherewith it is held, it is to be carried along the rite Groin ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king but a very ſlight compreſſion: then the hand that held on the dreſſing is to be removed, and with the help of both
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59957:89"/>hands this laſt end is conveighed under the girdle before, and on the right ſide, and then tied with the knot, called the Mariners knot; the ſame is done to the other end on the left ſide; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if both ends be long enough, after they have been brought under the Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, they are tied together by the Collar towards the left ſide, during the whole time that the bandage is uſed, a <hi>Ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere</hi> or Belly peace is to be applied to the Patient, and care had that the ends of the bandage keeps on the dreſſing of the Wound, for the Body of the band<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age muſt not deſcend lower than the left Buttock: afterwards the Thighs muſt be made faſt and kept at a moderate diſtance from one another with the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or thigh band tied together under the Knees, with the knot on the outſide to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Thighs.</p>
               <p>If it be a Woman that has been cut, the dreſſing is to be put upon the Belly as to Men, and the Pledget covered with Aſtringent upon the <hi>Orifice</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thra</hi> with a Plaiſter, Compreſs and the Frond or double T, of which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59957:90"/>a Girdle is to be made as with the Truſs, and the other ends which make the tailes of the T, paſſing betwixt the thighs, and croſſways upon the dreſſing, will hold it faſt, and preſs it as little as one pleaſes. When the Patient has a mind to make water, the bandage is to be taken off; they are not ſubject to ſo many accidents, and they are ſooner cured than Men.</p>
               <p>In Men the firſt dreſſing may be remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within twelve hours after the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat on, renewing the Imbrocation, with the ſame Aſtringent and the ſame Belly piece, for four or five days at leaſt or more, if the Belly be Swelled or Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; one may likewiſe make uſe of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of the Belly with rough Wine and Red Roſes, and ſometimes they are to be reiterated four or five times a day.</p>
               <p>The Wound is to be dreſſed with the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niment of <hi>Arceus</hi> half Melted, to make it Penetrate the more, with the Finger, or Feather of a Quill introduced to the very bottom of the Wound as gently as may be: then a little flat Pledget dipped in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59957:90"/>the ſame Liniment is to be applied upon the Lips of it, with a Trianglar Plaiſter, ſoaked in warm Oyl of Roſes, uſing a Compreſs, and a Truſs moiſtened with warm Oxycrat; and a clean dry <hi>Frond</hi> or bandage to be changed at every new dreſſing as at firſt: for the following days the Patients are to be dreſſed twice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very four and twenty hours, duly chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dreſſings, except that of the Belly, which may ſerve for the firſt days, and ever now and then the Patients are to be made dry; which is obſerved to be done when they are a dreſſing, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting to make them clean for avoiding a Gangrene. They are to be dreſſed with all ſpeed and diligence, and the Wound kept open as little as may be, having a fire always in the Room to correct the badneſs of the Air.</p>
               <p>After five or ſix days there is no more uſe made of Oxycrat, nor Aſtringent, nor of the Triangular Plaiſter, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a dry Belly piece; and in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion three or four drops of the Lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Arceus</hi> with a Feather or the Finger, and a flat Pledget upon the Lips
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59957:91"/>of the Wound. The Balſam of <hi>Peru,</hi> and of <hi>Capivei,</hi> which is called natural white Balſam, are Sovereign remedies for Agglutination; that of <hi>Capivei</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently good from the beginning to the very end. Some take equal parts of the Liniment of <hi>Arceus</hi> and the Oyl of Eggs, others make uſe of the Liniment of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus</hi> during the whole cure, others again of <hi>Capivei;</hi> ſome there are that make a Mixture of equal parts of <hi>Baſilicum,</hi> of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> Turpentine, and Oyl of Eggs, or the Liniment of <hi>Arceus,</hi> and the ſucceſs is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, provided the Operation hath been fortunate, and no bad accidents ſuperveen.</p>
               <p>Upon theſe Medicines a Pledget is put and a Plaiſter of <hi>Diacalciteos</hi> a little longer than the Wound, and of a breadth proportionable to the ſubject, a dry Truſs to bear up the Cods, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and a bandage upon the Wound, as has been before deſcribed, preſſing it a little harder than in the beginning: the <hi>Jarretiere</hi> or Thigh band is uſed till the cure be perfected. After the firſt days are over, it is proper to advertiſe the Patient to preſs with his hand a little
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59957:91"/>upon the dreſſing, that he may more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make water in his Urinal.</p>
               <p>Though the Wound of it ſelf requires conſolidation, yet care is to be had that the Lips and Teguments thereof turn not inwards; and after ſome days when the fluxion is over, or if none have happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the help of little and very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Compreſſes the Lips are to be kept equally raiſed, and a little diſtant, only at the <hi>Orifice</hi> of the Inciſion; for that purpoſe ſeveral Compreſſes are to be put near the Lip which is on the ſide of the left Thigh, to the end the bottom may conſolidate, before the Cicatrice be made. When one is ſure of the bottom, then he is to uſe deſiccatives upon a little Pledget, and ſeveral Compreſſes unequal in thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indifferently narrow, one on each ſide, and a Plaiſter to cover them, and over that another little Compreſs tranſverſly at the upper part of the Wound, and over theſe three, two others of unequal breadth, to keep the bandage, by that means, the faſter. If there grow up any fungous carnoſities, they are to be conſumed with calcined Alum, or with <hi>Lapis infernalis.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:59957:92"/>
               <p>There are ſome Patients that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a good conſtitution of Body are cured in eight, fifteen, or twenty days; but the ordinary time of curing <hi>Litho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy</hi> is thirty or forty days.</p>
               <p>It is prudence in a Chirurgeon to obſerve the alterations that happen to the Patient, that he may diſcover the bad Symptoms that we have mentioned, which change the method of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cure, and which require to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, or corrected by a particular me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod contrary to their Nature.</p>
               <p>This is performed by Diet, Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, and Medicines: the Diet, until the ſeventh or eighth day conſiſts in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from Wine, unleſs the Patient be very weak; he is to uſe a Tiſanne made of the ſhavings of Harts-Horn, and Ivory, or with a little Lint Seed, and the Roots of Mallows and Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, or at leaſt, in time of need, he is to drink of Chalybeat Water, or of the Tincture of Red Roſes, yet not according to his Thirſt, but a little leſs for fear of a Looſeneſs; it is enough that in four and twenty hours he take five or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59957:92"/>ſix meſſes of Broth, and very few Eggs: Blood-letting, and cooling and Anodyn Glyſters are good if he have a feaver, and pain in the lower Belly, but all by the advice of a Phyſician. And after the firſt ſeven or eight days are over, and that the Symptoms have ceaſed, his food is to be made ſtronger, beginning with Porrage, or Panadoes, then a little Meat and Bread, after that he hath been Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is commonly to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the fourteenth or fifteenth day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Operation.</p>
               <p>Chirurgery is neceſſary, when Blood letting is to be reiterated, abſceſſes and their <hi>Sinus</hi>'s opened, places where there is a diſpoſition towards putrifaction ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; ſometimes Cizars are made uſe of, to clip off Membranes and other parts that are wholly corrupted; Medicines are changed to diſcuſs tumors, and ripen Abſceſſes; the Ulcers of the <hi>Scrotum</hi> and Bladder are cleanſed by Injections and other Medicines that reſiſt morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and putrifaction. Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Symptoms appear before one another, or many together which make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication:
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59957:93"/>we ought therefore to ſpeak of the remedying of every one of them in particular.</p>
               <p>It hath been ſaid that Pain is mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by <hi>Oxyrrhodinum</hi> upon the Belly, the Groins, and the Cods; Hemorrhage by Aſtringents; a Feaver by Blood-let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, eſpecially if the Patient hath not loſt much Blood in the time of the Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or after, and if he have ſtrength: reſtleſneſs is conquered by cooling Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zems, Emulſions, and Soporificks after the firſt days; the inflammation of the parts after ſuppuration is extinguiſhed by the <hi>Ceratum</hi> of <hi>Galen,</hi> or by <hi>Nutritum;</hi> frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſmall Stones are voided with the Urine, and by the injection of warm Barley water, or they are extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the hook, the Extractor, <hi>Forceps,</hi> or the Scoop of the Button. The too great retention of Urine is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by paſſing the Womans Catheter into the Wound, and then by a Tent or Pipe left in it for ſome days; Gripings and Looſeneſs are ſtopped, by Anodyn and Carminative Glyſters, and by Juleps of Red Poppy, the Oyl of ſweet Almonds,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59957:93"/>Plantane Water, and Harts-Horn Jelly: Worms and Vermous matter the cauſe of their generation, are brought away by Medicines and Phyſick which help digeſtion, as thoſe into whoſe compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition enter, Rheubarb, Wormwood, Tamarinds, <hi>Aquila Alba</hi> in a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Ecchymoſes, Fluxion and moderate Tumors are diſſipated by reſolutives and diſcuſſing Plaiſters, by comfortative Cataplaſmes and Anodynes, according to the degrees of the evil, and the rules of Art, obſerving to apply more comfortatives, than ſimple Emolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents and diſcuſſives, becauſe of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity of the part: Abſceſſes are form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed commonly above the Inciſion and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times preſſing the head of the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor with one Finger, and the ſides with other two, the Purulent matter is Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated by the Wound; but if it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the skin is very thin, and the matter ready to burſt forth in a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, they are to be opened to the very bottom of the <hi>Sinus,</hi> and the cure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to Art. Deterſive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are made uſe of to mundifie and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:59957:94"/>cleanſe the Bladder; and Emulſions are given to the Patients, that the purulent matter may the more eaſily be evacuated.</p>
               <p>Excoriations and Itching are cured by <hi>Nutritum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum album Rhaſis,</hi> the Cerat of <hi>Galen; Pompholyx</hi> diſſolved in the Oyl of Roſes, and other deſiccative Anodynes, taking heed not to compreſs the bandage for ſome days; and if the Excoriations and Itching poſſeſs a great ſpace, the Patient might for ſome time be dreſſed without applying the Frond or Truſs, but only the Triangular Plaiſter covered with convenient Medicines, upon the Medicaments of the place where the Operation hath been made, making always uſe of the Thigh band to keep the Thighs at a convenient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from another. The ſame thing is to be practiſed when the <hi>Scrotum</hi> or Teſtacles are much ſwelled and in pain, and on that occaſion Anodyn and emol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lient Cataplaſms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſpread upon Linnen Cloath cut in the ſhape of the Plaiſter cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Plaiſter for the <hi>Scrotum,</hi> are to be made uſe of, with a bandage or ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59957:94"/>which is applied as in other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the Cods or Teſticles.</p>
               <p>Patients that are cut are ſubject to other accidents when they have lain long upon their Backs; they are to be remedied according to their kinds and degrees, and when they abate, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bandages are made uſe of, ſuch as the Truſs, Frond or double T. which is more proper in the end than in the beginning, becauſe it compreſſes more eaſily, and it is more commonly made uſe of for Women than for Men: to uſe it a right, the Girdle is to be put about the Patients Body, and one end of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried within the Collar, and both ends tied, one of the ends of the Tail of the T. is to be taken betwixt the Thighs, and making it paſs obliquely upon the dreſſing, it is tied to the Girdle in the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſide to that from whence it is taken; the ſame is to be done to the other end, faſtening them together by a kind of a knot called the Mariners knot, having a care not to ſtop up the paſſage of the <hi>Anus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:59957:95"/>
               <p>Fainting, Convulſion, and Vomiting, go often hand in hand together; but the laſt appears more frequently than the others; it is remedied by Wine, and by cordial Potions made of Treacle; the Confection of Hyacinth, Alkermes, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, prepared Pearle, Powder of Vipers, Syrup of Pomegranats, in Balm Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Scorzonera Water, <hi>Carduus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus,</hi> and Woodforell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various indications: theſe Medicines and the Doſe of them are to be choſen and determined according to the advice of a Phyſician, giving them at firſt in a ſmall quantity often renewed, becauſe of the debility of the Stomach.</p>
               <p>When the Vomiting is ſtopt; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion ceaſes, and the fainting is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſucculent nutriment, ſuch as good Gellies, ſtrong Broths, new laid Eggs which ſtrengthen the Patient if they ſtay with him: the reaſon is evident, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe inanition is the cauſe of theſe two Symptoms, and the Animal Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but in a ſmall quantity, prick the Nerves, which contract and draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Origination.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:59957:95"/>
               <p>The Wound does ſometimes foul, and by too great ſuppuration, according to <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Chauliac;</hi> it is obſerved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into a ſordid Ulcer, and moſt commonly virulent, becauſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimony of the Urine, and irritated Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that grow mordicant and biting. Theſe kinds of Ulcers are never without Inflammation, Itching, and Excoriation of the part: for ſuch accidents we are to make uſe of diverting, reſtraining and local Medicines, applied according to the Temperament of the part, and the counſel of the ſame Author, in the Chapter of Wounds with Hemorrhage: When many Symptoms appear together, the ſame Rule is to be obſerved, and to have regard to the order, the urgency and the cauſe, and eſpecially to that which is moſt urgent, amongſt other things carefully obſerving the effects of topical Medicines, wherein Chirurgery does moſt conſiſt.</p>
               <p>For curing of Diliriums and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headedneſs, ſtrong broths are given, minced meat made with Veal, Pullets, Partridges cut ſmall and put into an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59957:96"/>then Pot glazed, without water, well luted, and digeſted <hi>in Balneo Mariae;</hi> hearty food that is full of good Juyce, and of eaſie Concoction, for ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of the inanition, and temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Animal Spirits, the truth is a Dilirium with cold in the Extremities are of ſuch affinity, one with another, that they may be put into the ſame rank, and a Dilirium after <hi>Lithotomy</hi> is, as it were, the laſt degree of the Diſeaſe, the ſtrugling of Nature, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of the Iſchuria, or ſuppreſſion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</head>
               <p>THE Bladder is a Membranous part, that may be diſtended and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged by the quantity of matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, and when it is full or ſtimulated, that which is within opens the Sphincter that it may make to it ſelf a paſſage into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:59957:96"/>
               <p>When all things are in a natural ſtate, Man ſuffers no inconveniency becauſe the things contained within are in due time evacuated; but congealed Blood, or coagulated <hi>Pus,</hi> condenſed Seed, a Stone, a Fungous Body, groſs Humours, or Phlegm with Sand, one or more of the inferiour Vertebraes Luxated, hardened Excrements, a Child dead in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Womb, a Carnoſity or Calloſity ſometimes ſtop the Sphincter of the Bladder, or a place of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> it is the ſame when a Viſcous Humour cauſes a Numneſs of the Bladder, or when a Patient is in a dull and drouzie fit; which is occaſioned by a diverſion of ſenſation, an extaſie in the Brain, or a convulſion of the Nerve which goes from the <hi>Os ſacrum</hi> to the Sphincter of the Bladder, and by Malignant Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p>Beſides thoſe cauſes of ſuppreſſion of Urine which we have reckoned up, we are to take notice of the ſhrinking or flagging of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> to which Old Men are ſubject; the Compreſſion of the Neck of the Bladder cauſed by the falling
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:59957:97"/>down, or inflammation of the Matrix, or the Proſtates and Paraſtates, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>Hemorrhoide</hi> Veins, or by a great quantity of Urine which diſtends the Fibres of the Bladder, as is related by <hi>Pareus,</hi> L. XVII. of a Young Man, who having kept his Urine too long, fell into a ſuppreſſion though he had no Stone, and was cured by the Catheter. <hi>Fabrit. Hild.</hi> ſays, L. <hi>de Lith.</hi> Chap. 3. Col. I. that that excellent Mathematician <hi>Tycho-brahe</hi> being in a great aſſembly at <hi>Prague,</hi> where being forced to keep his water very long, he fell into ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Suppreſſion, that he could not be cured, but died of it.</p>
               <p>The retention of Urine, from what cauſe ſoever it proceed, produces a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Pain, and inſupportable inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all the Neighbouring parts of the Bladder, from whence a ſuppreſſion is occaſioned, becauſe the Urine is not voided, and that it is continually aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in quantity. In that caſe Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents are all over in a heat, their eyes look red, their face burning, have an Oppreſſion, Reſtleſneſs, Feaver, a hard,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59957:97"/>painful and very large Swelling above the <hi>Pubis;</hi> bilious Vomitings, and all theſe troubleſome Symptoms reduce them to ſuch a ſtate, that without ſpeedy help, they expect nothing but death.</p>
               <p>The Chirurgeon will know that it is a clot of Blood that is the cauſe of the Suppreſſion, if the Patient hath been lately Wounded in the Kidneys, or hath piſſed Blood; if an Ulcer in the Kidneys has preceded, and the Patient hath made Purulent water, he may conjecture that a collection of thick and viſcous <hi>Pus</hi> is the cauſe of it: if the ſigns of the Stone have appeared, he is to acquaint the by-ſtanders with it, he may diſcern it from a <hi>Fungus</hi> by the Catheter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Stone be wrapped in a Coat; he may know if it be a Carnoſity or Calloſity, by means of the Catheter or a ſearing Candle. I ſay nothing of the Patients manner of living, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes may have been the cauſe of ſharp Humours, or a great inflammation: nor ſhall I neither ſpeak of other cauſes which manifeſt themſelves. Now if many cauſes of Suppreſſion joyn together, the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59957:98"/>diverſity of Symptoms will ſerve for a ſign to make the Prognoſtick by.</p>
               <p>The Patient cannot for many days en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a Suppreſſion, without being much weakened and in danger. When it is cauſed by a falling down of the Matrix, there is no more to be done, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that part; when the <hi>Hemorrhoides</hi> preſs the Neck of the Bladder, they muſt be opened with a Lancet or Leeches; the Numneſs of the Bladder is remedied by a grain of Salt or Nitre put into the paſſage of the Urine, or with a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>Mel Roſatum</hi> and the Powder of <hi>Hiera,</hi> or the Oyl of Scorpions: when there is congealed Blood, Purulent Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or thick Phlegm in the Bladder, we may make uſe of an injection of <hi>Oxymel</hi> with the Oyl of ſweet Almonds; in the Flagging of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> hollow Wax Candles are imployed; if there happen any Carnoſity or Calloſity in it, they are incided and eaten off, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward a Leaden Pipe introduced into the place. When one hath kept his water too long, if he be afraid of being ſearched, bags of Pellitory of the Wall
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59957:98"/>moiſtened with the Oyl of Capers or of Turpentine are to be laid upon the <hi>Pubis;</hi> and if he do not find eaſe upon that, he is to be perſwaded to ſuffer the intromiſſion of the Catheter. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation of the Rectum, the Matrix and Proſtates is allayed by Blood-letting, and Glyſters of Oxycrat, Pellitory Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the Decoction of it with <hi>Mel Roſatum,</hi> and a Bath of warm Water.</p>
               <p>For all ſuppreſſions of Urine, when there is no other apparent diſeaſe, it is of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular advantage to let Blood, give cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glyſters and Bath; becauſe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are cauſed by meer inflammation, and the weakneſs to which the Patient is reduced, does often laxat the parts, and make way for the Emiſſion of Urine, the retention whereof puts him in danger of Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> 13. of the <hi>Meth.</hi> before <hi>Pareus</hi> L. 17. C. 37. adviſes not to give Diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, nor ſtrong purgatives before Blood-letting; becauſe they may acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate the motion of Humours, or of Praeternatural Bodies towards the Bladder, and fill it fuller, whilſt the obſtruction
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59957:99"/>of the Sphincter hinders the evacuation of the Urine.</p>
               <p>But though all remedies have been uſed; yet ſometimes the Patient is not eaſed; in that caſe if he cannot be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the diſtemper be very urgent, it is better without delaying ſeveral days, to bring him to conſent to be cut, if he be troubled with the Stone. And if it be only Urine retained through an inflammation of the Sphincter, or by a thick and viſcuous matter, it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Prick or Tap the <hi>Perineum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of the Puncture or Tapping of the <hi>Perineum.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is to be ſuppoſed that the Patient hath found no eaſe from all the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines that have been adminiſtred unto him, and that the ſuppreſſion continues with ſuch Symptoms as give ground to a ſad Prognoſtick, and call for ſpeedy relief to the Patient.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:59957:99"/>
               <p>The great relation that there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> and the Pricking or Tapping of the <hi>Perineum,</hi> gives us ground to propoſe three ways of Practiſing it; and ſeeing they have no proper names we ſhall diſtinguiſh them by thoſe of the various Methods of <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> to wit, the Hight, the Great, and the leſſer Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>Though it hath been ſaid, that the High Operation is not in uſe, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs it would ſeem that the great Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor above the <hi>Pubis,</hi> cauſed by the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Urine, eſpecially in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuated Patient, might render the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration eaſie, without any fear of hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the parts of the lower Belly; and that for that purpoſe, having Prickt the Tumor with a Lance as deep as the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der without Tying the Patient, it will be ſufficient to introduce a Wire or Stilet, that may ſerve for a conductor to a crooked and convenient Pipe, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it into its cavity.</p>
               <p>The High Operation of Tapping the <hi>Perineum</hi> may likewiſe be practiſed by means of a Trocart with which the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59957:100"/>Punction may be made in the Tumor above the <hi>Pubis;</hi> it may be certainly known when the Bladder is open, &amp; then a Wire is to be paſſed into it; and having pulled out the Trocart, the Wire will ſerve for a Conductor to the Pipe, juſt ſo as to the Parakenteſis or Tapping of People in Dropſies. We ſhall give the deſcription of this Trocart, and of the manner of uſing it, when we come to ſpeak of the third way of Pricking and Tapping the <hi>Perineum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond way that is in uſe: is the great Operation, as I have ſeen it practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by men of great skill and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe method I have followed. There needs no more but a Pipe or <hi>Canula</hi> mounted, a ſmall Tent propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionated to the Cavity of the Pipe, two Plaiſters, and two Compreſſes the one a little bigger than the other.</p>
               <p>All things being in readineſs, and the Patient ſeated in poſture and held as for <hi>Lithotomy;</hi> to be more aſſured of the way that muſt be taken in making the Inciſion the furrowed Catheter is to be paſſed into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> as far up as it
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59957:100"/>can go, without forcing any thing; if the inflammation be moderate, or if there be no carnoſity, nor other obſtacles, it is to be introduced into the Bladder: A Servant or the Chirurgeon himſelf may hold the Catheter, and he is to obſerve all circumſtances as in cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Stone, making the Inciſion lower than for <hi>Lithotomy,</hi> and ſhorter upon the ſlit or furrowing; into which he is to thruſt the Bill of the Gorgeret, to introduce it the more eaſily into the Bladder. It is fit that the furrowing continue like a gutter, without any thing to ſtop it at the Bill or Extremity of the Catheter; the voiding of Urine is a certain ſign that the Gorgeret is in the Bladder; and then the Catheter is to be diſengaged and ſoftly pulled out. The Chirurgeon is to hold the Gorgeret in one hand, and in the other, the Tent or Pipe mounted with the end dipped in Oyl, and he is to conduct it into the Bladder, by means of the Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geret, or in defect of that, if it be come out of the Bladder, he may take the Button with a Scoop, and uſe it as
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59957:101"/>hath been ſaid already. If there be no Button, one may make uſe of a big Wire, which being introduced into the Bladder, will ſerve for a conductor to the Tent or Pipe.</p>
               <p>Though one could not paſs the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed Catheter into the Bladder before the Operation yet it will eaſily enter after the Inciſion, becauſe that little Blood that is ſpilt, will diſſipate the Spirits which cauſed the inflammation and tenſion in the parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tavenin</hi> Chap. 121. of his Operations propoſes, not to introduce the Catheter, but the Patient being put into a poſture to make the Inciſio with a <hi>Biſtory</hi> betwixt the <hi>Anus</hi> and <hi>Scrotum,</hi> on the ſide of the Seam or Suture, in the ſame place that it is made in for <hi>Lithotomy;</hi> being come, (ſays he) near the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it is to be opened, thruſting the <hi>Biſtory</hi> or Lancet boldly up, until that the Urine come out, then the Tent is introduced, and ſo the Operation is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
               <p>It is not convenient to evacuate all the Urine, if it was exceſſive in quantity;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:59957:101"/>becauſe too great evacuations are always hurtful, according to <hi>Hippoc.</hi> Book 2. of his Aphoriſms; but having voided as much as may conſiſt with the ſtrength of the Patient, with a little piece of Linnen Cloth one may ſtop the Orifice of the Tent or Pipe, and having put a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs upon it, ſome Body is to hold his hand thereon, aſſiſting the Patient to Bed; then lay upon the Tent a thick Pledget covered with Aſtringent, a little Plaiſter; another moderate Compreſs, and over that the Triangular Plaiſter cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed likewiſe with Aſtringent, and another Compreſs ſtill upon the Plaiſter, a Truſs to bear up the Cods, and the Frond or double T. with the Thigh-band, as hath been deſcribed. The bandage that is only contentive, hinders not but that a little Urine may come out; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when the Patient hath reſted and taken refreſhment, he is to make Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter through the Tent without pulling of it out.</p>
               <p>In dreſſing the Patient the Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to examine if it be a <hi>Fungus</hi> which cauſed the ſuppreſſion; and he may
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59957:102"/>know that, by the Finger or the ſtreight Catheter, by inſpection into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is voided with the Urine, or by the injection of warm barly Water, Deterſives and the other Medicaments that are uſed in dreſſing ſuch a Patient. If a Stone be felt, it is to be extracted with the Scoop, the Hook or the <hi>Forceps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fungus</hi>'s are fetched off by injections; if it be an Ulcer, proper remedies for cleanſing it are to be uſed. An inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is more eaſily cured than any other diſtemper, becauſe many times it is kept in being by the retention of the Urine. When the cauſe of the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is removed, the intention of the Artiſt ought to be the reuniting of the parts: And therefore the Tent is drawn out, and the Patients are dreſſed like thoſe that are cut of the Stone, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the general cure, if no accidents appear, or the particular method, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medying every Symptome.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of surgical instruments</figDesc>
                  <p>page 153</p>
               </figure>
               <p>This Trocart may be made of vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kinds of Metal, excepting the point, which ought to be of Steel; it is ſeven or eight Inches in length, that it may be the more commodious for uſe, and as big as an ordinary quill: in the ſhape of it ſeveral things are to be conſidered; for the end of it which is of Steel, is of a Pyramidal and Triangular Figure. This point is about a Fingers breadth in length; in one ſide of it there is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing that reaches from the point, or very near it, to the other end of the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:59957:104"/>Trocart, and becauſe of that furrowing the Inſtrument in its length repreſents a ſtreight Catheter for making Inciſion, becauſe it is hollow on the one ſide and round on the other, which is the out ſide of it. The Pyramide of Steel tapers and grows ſmaller from the baſis till ye come to the point, but from that baſis to the other end of the Trocart it is alike in bigneſs.</p>
               <p>The Wire or <hi>Stilet</hi> is ſtraight, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently ſmall, of the ſame bigneſs all along, and ſupple and pliant, about eight Inches long, proportionable to the furrowing of the Trocart.</p>
               <p>The mounted Tent, that is uſed in this Operation, may be crooked for the high and ſtraight for the leſſer Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Punction of the Bladder, long and ſmall in proportion to the Groſſneſs and Age of the Patient, that ſo the end may be thurſt into the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without making too great a <hi>Solutio Continui</hi> it is to be obſerved that the end of the Tent, where its eyes are, ought to be proportioned to the middle part of the Pyramide of the Trocart,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:59957:104"/>that it may eaſily enter into the Orifice of the Punction, and that the body of that Tent be of a Conick Figure, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bigger and bigger by degrees, as it comes nearer the head where the Rings are, though the extremity of the Tent, were ſmaller, yet it might ſuffice for conveighing of the Urine; but it would be uſeleſs, if ſome more thick and viſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matter were contained in the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>In uſing of theſe three Inſtruments; when the Patient is ſituated in the poſture that hath been ſaid, the Cods are lifted up,, and having marked the place where the Punction is to be made in the <hi>Perineum</hi> on the ſide of the Seam or Suture, the Trocart is thruſt in, and ſinking the end by which it is held, the ſlit or furrowing being upwards, the Pyramide is to be thruſt on forwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Body of the Bladder, which being much diſtended, is therefore eaſily opened.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as the Trocart is within, the Urine will come running out by the furrowing, and the Wire is to be taken,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:59957:105"/>and conducted into the Bladder by the ſame furrowing; afterward the Trocart is drawn out, in place whereof, holding the Wire in one hand, the Tent mounted is to be taken, and paſſing the Wire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its Cavity, it is to be made to ſlide along the ſame. When the Tent is near to the <hi>Perineum,</hi> the Wire is to be taken by the end, and the Tent at the ſame time conducted into the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we may know that it is in, when the Urine comes out at its Cavity: And then the Wire is pulled out; and as much Urine ſuffered to be voided as may be thought convenient, other things being to be performed as in the other manner called the great Operation. This Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cart has one thing that is ſingular, which is, that ſo ſoon as the extremity of its ſlit is in the place where the Water is, the Urine is voided, without any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being thruſt too far in.</p>
               <p>There are ſome who make uſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trocart for the ſame Operation this has a ſolid and round point of Steel about a Fingers breadth in length; others cauſe it to be made Triangular, or a little ſlat and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:59957:105"/>two-edged; but ſtill proportioned to the Tent or Pipe, the inſtrument in its length is ſtreight and hollow, and has two openings near the baſis of its point; that Inſtrument is paſſed into the Tent, and in that poſture the punction is made, the opening of which is always leſs than the Orifice of the Tent; and it cannot be introduced without great pain to the Patient; beſides, this Trocart muſt be Thruſt deeper in than the other, before the Urine can be perceived to come out. All men are free to examin and try thoſe things, and to chooſe what pleaſes them beſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe Trocarts may ſerve for other Operations, as in a kind of Hydrocele, where the Waters are gathered together, without being ſtilled into the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Membranes; in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenteſis; or even in making perforations through the Skin, and paſſing the Silk and Stones becauſe about three or four fingers breadth from one end of the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cart that was firſt deſcribed, a hole may be made like the eye of a great Needle through which the Silk may be paſſed.</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:59957:106"/>
               <p>Every time that it hath been uſed, it muſt be new ſet, for the Urine blunts the edges very much. It is good to practiſe ſuch kind of Operations upon dead Bodies: for that end, one muſt with a Syringe Squirt as much matter as poſſibly he can, into the Bladder, then tie a Ligature about the Yard, and make the Punction as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and then make a diſſection of the Bladder, to obſerve what hath been done, that ſo he may take his meaſures for another time.</p>
               <p>We may avoid offending the <hi>Rectum</hi> by conducting the point of the Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mide towards the Bladder, which then is much diſtended, and we need not fear to open it in the Body, becauſe theſe Wounds are not abſolutely Mortal. And though they are ſaid to be harder to conſolidate in the Membranous part thereof, nevertheleſs we ſhould baniſh ſuch apprehenſions, becauſe we ſee by experience that they are cured, and that the buſineſs is to ſave the life of a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:59957:106"/>
               <p>They to whom Fiſtula's do remain after the Punction of the <hi>Perineum,</hi> make uſe of a Tent which they cauſe to be opened, and ſtopt now and then for the voiding of the Urine: they may be made to ſtop with a Screw for greater ſecurity. The ends of the Linnen Cloth or Languet of the Tent; are tied the one before, and the other behind to a Girdle, held up by a Collar, like thoſe which have been deſcribed when we ſpoke of the bandage of the Yard for a <hi>Phimoſis</hi> Chap. X. If ſome Symptom of <hi>Lithotomy</hi> ſucceed the Punction of the <hi>Perineum,</hi> it is to be remedied ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its kind; and when none ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, or if they be cured, the Patient and Chirurgeon may have good hopes, and both doing their duties, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal aſſiſtances the <hi>Lithotomy</hi> and Punction of the <hi>Perineum</hi> are brought to a perfect cure. Nevertheleſs what care ſoever the Chirurgeon may have, and how obedient, confiding and quiet, ſo ever the Patient may prove, aſſiſted as he ought to be by thoſe who attend him, and the adminiſtration of proper
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:59957:107"/>Medicines, yet ſometimes he hath the trouble to be incommoded by the other diſtempers contained in the following Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of diſeaſes that happen after cutting for the Stone, and of the way of curing them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Y</hi> of <hi>Chauliack</hi> in his ſecond Treatiſe ſays, that if there be no Metaſtaſis of the Humours into Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemes, they are terminated by Diſcuſſion, Suppuration, Obduration and putrifaction and afterward he ſpeaks of the manner of treating and curing them. This ſhews that there is a difference betwixt their term, their curing and their cure, the end of one diſeaſe may be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of another; the cure hath an uncertain end, though healing be that which is propoſed according to Art; we ſee but too many inſtances of this in thoſe that are troubled with the Stone; that evil is terminated by the extraction of the Stone; and that Stone taken
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:59957:107"/>out, or that the diſtemper ended by the Operation, produces a Wound, or other accidents, the cure of which is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and which nevertheleſs do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways terminate in a cure, but ſometimes in a new Stone, a Fiſtula in the <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum,</hi> an involuntary ſpilling of the Water, a preternatural voiding of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or in many diſeaſes together; they have each of them their Cauſes, Differences, Signs, Prognoſticks and Ways of Curing.</p>
               <p>We ſhall ſay nothing as to the Stone which may be obſerved after that the Patient hath been under cure; we muſt only take notice that the cauſe of it may be this, that there is a Quarry in the Kidneys, which from time to time fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes the Bladder with Stones, and then the Operation ought to be delayed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Patient be fully recovered in ſtrength, the ſeaſon be favourable, or that the accidents be remedied; And above all the Patient had need of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great ſtock of reſolution to endure a ſecond cutting.</p>
               <p>The Fiſtula in the <hi>Perineum</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:59957:108"/>of we ſpeak is a Sinuous Ulcer below the <hi>Scrotum,</hi> with a Calloſity along the length of it, by which the Urine iſſues out. It is cauſed by the Chirurgeons fault, or by the Patients, by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of accidents, or indeed by many things concurring, when the Chirurgeon and Patient do not do their duties, and that bad and violent Symptoms appear in the time, or a little after the Operation.</p>
               <p>By the fault of the Chirurgeon; when in the beginning he ſuffers the Lips of the Ulcer to be to ſoon joyned together, before he be certain that the Bottom of it is deterſed and agglutinated, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no accidents appearing he hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Bottom of it to much, and that he hath not had care after the firſt eight or ten days at moſt were over, moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Compreſs the bandage, and to make uſe of ſmall and very narrow Compreſſes laid upon the two ſides of the Inciſion.</p>
               <p>On the part of the Patient, when his Urine being too ſharp corrodes the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and hinders the reunion, or that he lies not ſtill as he ought, not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:59957:108"/>Directions, and not ſuffering himſelf to be treated according to the rules of Art; to which muſt be added his being emaciated, the abundance of Urine, and if he moderate not his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or exceed in his food, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities whereof cauſes a too long ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puration.</p>
               <p>The moſt remarkable accidents that contribute to the Fiſtula, are a Putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, which cauſes great loſs of ſubſtance in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts; an Ulcer in the Bladder, or Kidneys, the ſuppuration whereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that the parts be kept dilated.</p>
               <p>The differences of theſe Fiſtula's are drawn from hence, that ſome of them are even and ſtraight from the Skin to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> without any other profound or ſuperficial ſinuoſity, and are apparent on the ſide of the ſeam; others have their <hi>Orifice</hi> in the <hi>Rectum;</hi> ſome are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with great loſs of ſubſtance, others have one or more ſinuoſities in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and in the neighbouring parts, or otherwiſe they happen in a bad ſubject; and theſe differences are
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:59957:109"/>diſcovered, if it be obſerved in time of dreſſing the Patient, that thirty or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days after the Operation, the Ulcer cicatriſes, except one or more little paſſages, or a ſmall Lump or Tubercle, which is named, <hi>the Pullets rump</hi> on the ſide of the ſeam, through which the Urine eſcapes; or if the Patient being much extenuated, the ſuperveening ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents have cauſed a great loſs of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> or that new Fleſh cannot breed; the iſſuing of the Urine by the <hi>Anus</hi> makes it apparent that the <hi>Orifice</hi> of the Fiſtula is in the <hi>Rectum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Fiſtula's in the <hi>Perineum</hi> are not alike hard to be cured; for the firſt kind may be taken into cure, provided there be no great loſs of ſubſtance, and that the ſubject be good, the reſt being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly incurable; ſome of thoſe who are troubled with Fiſtula's have this comfort that they do not always run. If the ſubject be good, not too lean, and the Ulcer filled with well conditioned Fleſh, the cure of the Fiſtula may without interruption be undertaken: but if the Patient be extenuated, or if there be
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:59957:109"/>great loſs of ſubſtance in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> with Callous Fleſh, the cure is not to be attempted, until the ſtrength be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, that it may be tryed if new Fleſh can be procured. In that caſe he muſt be comforted, giving him hopes that at another time he may be cured. Thoſe that have their <hi>Orifice</hi> in the <hi>Rectum</hi> are ſometimes leſs troubleſome and they are not to be tampered with.</p>
               <p>For curing of the Fiſtula, we ſhall not ſpeak in this place of the univerſal regiment, we ſuppoſe that to have been obſerved, either whil'ſt the Patient was under cure for the Stone, or ſince, but we ſhall only treat of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar management of that cure. Authors ſpeak of Potions and many Topical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines for the cure of Fiſtula's: but ſince my deſign is only to deſcribe what I have obſerved to have been ſucceſsful, I can affirm that many have been cured by the following means; which conſiſts in introducing into the Bottom of the Fiſtula, a Catheretick Trochiſque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the laſt Chapter; next the falling off of the Eſcar is to be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:59957:110"/>by Baſilicum; and then the Patient is to be dreſſed like one that hath been cut of the Stone after the ſeventh or eighth day; ſome make uſe at the ſame time of a deſiccative Wax Candle, which they thruſt into the Yard up to the bottom of the Fiſtula: others cure them without the uſe of Wax Candles; when any accident appears, it is to be remedied, as hath been ſaid Chap. XIX.</p>
               <p>If thoſe that are fiſtulous are to be pitied, they who are troubled with an unvoluntary emiſſion of their water by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> ought alſo to be ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Miſerable, as thoſe alſo, who piſs not at all: But they from whom the groſs Excrements drop againſt their will, ſurpaſs the reſt in Miſery. What may be ſaid then, if one ſhould ſuffer many of theſe Inconveniences at the ſame time?</p>
               <p>The ſpilling of the Water is cauſed by a Palſie in the Sphincter of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by the Inciſion of its Fibres, or by a great Dilaceration, when a big and rough ſtone hath too much widened the Paſſage, and hath cauſed a Suppuration of long continuance.</p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:59957:110"/>
               <p>The Kinds and Differences are taken from the Greatneſs or Smalneſs of the Emiſſion; the Signs of it are viſible, or rather moſt ſenſible and uneaſie to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, becauſe Shame and Vexation hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them ſometimes from ſeeking a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; from whence the Prognoſtick may be made, That all of them are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly hard to be cured, the moſt part incurable; and that the Cure moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is but palliative.</p>
               <p>Women are not ſubject to Fiſtula's, but only to this ſpilling of their Water, which is more uneaſie to them, than to men, becauſe of the Conformation of their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and that their Sex which hath Modeſty for its Property, obliging them to a greater reſervedneſs, hinders them from ſeeking relief: and this makes them to have Clouts or Spunges about them to receive the Water, or to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy ſomething elſe, that Neceſſity and Uneaſineſs ſuggeſt to them.</p>
               <p>When the Spilling of Urine remains with men, they may have recourſe to a little Engine, ſuch as I ſaw in the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Perſon, whoſe Character and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:59957:111"/>Quality allows me not to name him; I have heard him ſay, that it was very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and commodious for him.</p>
               <p>That Engine is made of Steel, Iron, or any other convenient Metal: It is compoſed of two parts, each about three Inches long, and a Fingers breadth wide; one of the two pieces bends a little in its Longitude, and the other is ſtraight; theſe two pieces joyn together at one end with a turning joynt like a Compaſs, and at the other end both are bent back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to faſten within one another, ſo that preſſing with the Finger, they may be opened and ſhut. Theſe two pieces are covered with Linnen, as much, or as little as one pleaſes; afterward the Yard is put into that Inſtrument, obſerving to keep the crooked part uppermoſt; and when one hath made water, it is ſhut: the Compreſſion may be made as ſlightly as one pleaſes, covering or facing the Engine more or leſs, that it may be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without Pain, &amp; letting the Urine paſs through, which in ſome manner ſupplies the action of the Sphincter of the Bladder.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen ſome who have made uſe
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:59957:111"/>of Boxes of White Lattin, or other Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Leather made in form of an Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, tied to a Girdle, and wherein the Nut always hung, which is not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pain and Trouble. There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtrument much like to a Truſs, for ruptures; it is made like the Steel Truſſes, having a Girdle of the ſame Faſhion, and on the left ſide, in ſtead of a Bolſter, the end of the Girdle bends Elbow-ways downwards, and terminates in the ſhape of a ſmall Iron Plate, which is covered with Felt, Leather, or Cork, ſufficiently waxed over, that it may be of a convex Figure like an Olive, and indifferently hard, that it may exactly anſwer to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> above and near to the place where the Inciſion hath been made. When the Bandage is applied, the little Eminence preſſes the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra</hi> below the Cods, and to keep it firm, it is made faſt by the other end, where there is a ſtrap of Leather of the ſame faſhion as in the Steel Truſſes for Ruptures; and beſides, if a man were troubled with a falling down of the Inteſtines, one of theſe Truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might be made on purpoſe for him,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:59957:112"/>where there might be a Bolſter for the Rupture, and the little eminence for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rethra,</hi> and hindring the ſhedding of the Water. Though this Bandage or Truſs be in effect only for a palliative Cure of this Diſtemper, yet it may ſometimes ſerve for a real Cure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hereby the parts gather ſtrength, and are corroborated.</p>
               <p>There is another kind of Bandage ſtill, the Girdle whereof is made of Fuſtian, and that part which is to paſs upon the <hi>Pubis</hi> of a piece of Wood of the length and bigneſs of the Patients Finger, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Fuſtian and Wax, betwixt which and the <hi>Pubis,</hi> the Yard being compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, lyes along looking upwards; that Poſture hinders the ſpilling of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The ſame Bandage hath Points faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the fore part of it, that they may be carried betwixt the Thighs, and tied ſide-ways to the Girdle, that ſo the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage may not riſe too high.</p>
               <p>Involuntary voiding of the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is cauſed ſometimes by the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons Fault, if in time of Lithoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my he make the Inciſion too low, and if
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:59957:112"/>he cut the <hi>Rectum,</hi> eſpecially in the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Operation, if he take not good heed; moſt frequently the violent Motions of the Patient contribute to it, but much more Putrifaction, Abſceſſes, or other Accidents that follow the Operation.</p>
               <p>Their Kinds, Signs, and Prognoſticks, are taken from the more or leſs Eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the Excrements by the remaining Fiſtula, which is far more uneaſie than the ſpilling of the Water, or the Fiſtula alone. The Cure of this ſtercoral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion is impoſſible, when it is cauſed by Inciſion of the upper part of the Sphincter of the <hi>Rectum,</hi> or when there is great loſs of Subſtance; if any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take ſuch Patients into Cure, they are to obſerve the Method of curing Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtula's in the <hi>Anus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We need not enlarge to prove, that theſe kinds of Diſtempers may have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Cauſes concurring at the ſame time; when many of theſe Indiſpoſitions hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen together, we muſt have our recourſe to the Method of curing complicated Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, as well for the Prognoſtick Part, as for the order of the Complications.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:59957:113"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of Medicines to prevent the Stone, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of the Stone, and of Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for dreſſing thoſe that are cut.</head>
               <p>THough we promiſed to enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Medicines that may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Stone; we muſt, however, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that it is very difficult, and perhaps impoſſible to determine preciſely where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they do conſiſt; becauſe the moſt learned in natural Diſcoveries, ſpeak on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in general of the Figures of Bodies, and Microſcopes have not been able to make known the particular Nature of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, nor yet of all their Pores. Poſſibly we might ſucceed without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving all theſe Particularities; for though Enquiries into Nature were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued to that very point, yet ſtill there would be cauſes that did not depend on us, and which might form the Stone; the Bigneſs, Figure, Number, and Motion of the Particles of Bodies of which we are compoſed, and of thoſe which ſerve us for Food, are no ways in our power; though theſe things be ſufficient to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:59957:113"/>in us the Maladies that we fear, if the Secretions and Excretions be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to the Courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. That we may reap Benefit from the Miſeries of others, it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that they who are moſt ſubject to the Gravel or Stone, live after ſuch a manner, as may be avoided, or at leaſt corrected by other means; and ſeeing we have ſpoken of fenny and marſhy Places, groſs and thick Air, calculous Food, muddy Waters, and of the Exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that may much debilitate the Parts of the Body, they are carefully to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, uſing moderately thoſe things that are for our Nouriſhment, following Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes ſuitably to our ſtrength, without affecting too much Niceneſs and Delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: It were better to uſe a little too much, than not enough; becauſe Life conſiſts in Action, and men love them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too well, not to repoſe and take their Reſt; if we be not guilty of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, the Parts of our Body continue in good Health, ready to reſiſt all attacks.</p>
               <p>Though few things contribute more to the forming of the Stone in the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:59957:114"/>than continuing long without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Water, yet we muſt not at firſt give Diureticks, but only gentle Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to empty the Inteſtines and adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parts: of that kind are <hi>Manna, Caſſia, Catholicum duplex, Lenitive Electuary, Diaprunum ſimplex;</hi> a day or two after, <hi>Turpentine</hi> prepared in this faſhion, may be given in drink: Take an Ounce, or Six Drachms of the beſt <hi>Turpentine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſhed, diſſolve it in a Mortar with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the yelk of an Egg, then add to it two or three ounces of the Water of Winter-Cherries, Smallage, Pelletory of the Wall, or of ſome other Liquor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nature of the Diſeaſe, and the ſtate of the Patient: Stir all together that it may be exactly mixed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of ſo white a Colour, that it looks like Cream or coagulated Milk. <hi>Bever. C.</hi> XI. of the Stone of the Kidneys and Bladder. The Bath gives eaſe to thoſe that are troubled with the Stone, and contributes much to the bringing away of little ſtones that ſtop in the Kidneys and Bladder.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:59957:114"/>
               <p>The uſe of the following Ptiſanne, or Barley-water, is very good againſt the ſame Diſtempers: It is made with an Ounce of <hi>Linſeed,</hi> and the Roots of Mallows and Marſhmallows, of each two Ounces, put into five quarts of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter boyled away to four; into three Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Ptiſanne may be dropped four or five Drops of the Spirit of Sulphur, and it may be made ſtronger by augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Doſe of the Ingredients in the ſame quantity of water: It is approved of for making one void Water, mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pain, and bringing away Stones.</p>
               <p>The two following Receipts were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me by <hi>Monſieur Jonnot,</hi> the firſt of which, he told me, hath often (to his Experience) been ſucceſsful in eaſing Nephritick Pains, and thoſe who are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to void ſmall Stones; and that the ſecond never failed him, provided the Stone be of a Bigneſs fit to come out of the <hi>Pelvis,</hi> or Baſon of the Kidneys.</p>
               <p>The firſt Medicine is to be taken in the Spring and Fall, every Morning for three days together. Take ſix Ounces of the Water of Pelletory of the Wall, an
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:59957:115"/>Ounce of the Oyl of ſweet Almonds, and an Ounce and a Half of the Syrup of Limons; in caſe of neceſſity, it is taken at any time.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond Remedy, the Patient muſt be once or twice blooded, and twice purged with two or three Drachms of <hi>Sena</hi> infuſed overnight in the Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Dogs-graſs, Roots of Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, and a little bundle of Flax; to the Colature of which muſt be added an Ounce of cleaned <hi>Caſſia</hi> for every Doſe: The day after he is to make uſe of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Limonade, and is to continue it three days ſucceſſively in the waning of the Moon, faſting three or four Hours after.</p>
               <p>Take of Argentine, or Wild Tanſey, Water Lentils and Creſſes, of each one Handful, let them boil half a quarter of an hour in a quart of water, when it is taken off the Fire, add to it the Juice and Rind of three or four Limons; let all infuſe together for the Space of four Hours, then ſtrain it, and add thereunto three Ounces of the Powder of Sugar-Candy, and twenty Grains of the Spirit
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:59957:115"/>of Salt: Keep it for the Uſe aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The Garden-flags, or blew <hi>Flower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-luce</hi> that grows upon Walls, infuſed cold into what quantity one pleaſes of White-wine, and an Ounce of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, taken for the firſt time by Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ten or twelve Years of Age, brings away the Stone: The Doſe is to be increaſed or diminiſhed, according to the Age of the Patient and its Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, giving always too little, rather than too much, for fear of drawing the Stones in too great abundance towards the Sphincter of the Bladder, which would cauſe a ſuppreſſion of Urine. One may renew it two or three days after, and Purge by the Advice of a Phyſician. The uſe of White-wine, Raddiſh-water, and Wine made of the Fruit of Eglan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, or Sweet Briar, taken now and then, is good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> in the end of the Preface to his ſecond Treatiſe of his great Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, preſcribes for remedying the ſuppreſſion of Urine, the uſe of the ſtones that are found in the Heads of Crabs, beat into a ſubtil Powder, drank in the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:59957:116"/>Juice or Water of Raddiſhes, and if the Patients do not thereby make water, to make a little bag of Saffron, and lay it upon the Kidneys, or the Belly, towards the paſſage of the Ureters, and upon the <hi>Perinaeum:</hi> Or to make a Powder of dried Acorns, and give it to be drank in the Water or Juice of Raddiſhes, in what quantity the Phyſician ſhall judge fit.</p>
               <p>The two following Medicines are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of for bringing away of Sand and ſmall Stones. In the wain of the Moon, the Patient being Purged, let him take in the Morning the bigneſs of a Nut of freſh Butter, and ſwallow it down like a Pill; then let him take a four Limon, and ſqueeze out the Juice of it into four Ounces of White-wine, let him drink that Potion a quarter of an hour after that he hath ſwallowed the Butter: This may be reiterated two or three days after, according to its effect, and then Purge again.</p>
               <p>For the ſame effect, take a little white Onion, cut it into ſmall pieces, infuſe them over Night upon hot Embers in four Ounces of White-wine, and ſtrain
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:59957:116"/>it; having taken the ſame quantity of freſh Butter in the manner above directed, a quarter of an hour after drink of this Infuſion; it is more violent than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. The Butter is taken firſt, that the Stomack may not be ſtung, or too much pricked by the Wine, the Limon-juice, or the Onion: And it is to be obſerved, that if the Patient ſhould but once take a greater quantity than theſe Doſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, inſtead of giving eaſe, it would expoſe him to a ſuppreſſion again, becauſe theſe Medicines are very Diuretick, and carry rapidly along with them what they meet with in their way.</p>
               <p>They ſay that Jet hath ſo much Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that it is enough to hang it about the Arm, or to carry it in ones Pocket, to obtain eaſe of Nephritick pains, and to bring away the Gravel and Stone.</p>
               <p>The cold infuſion of Nephritick Wood is Excellent; put what quantity of that Wood you pleaſe into water, to which it will give a Tincture; take of it two Glaſſes in the Morning, and one at Night, or at any other hour of the day, if the Stomack be empty; this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:59957:117"/>aſſwages the pain, and brings away Sand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pareus,</hi> Book 17. Chap. 37. deſcribes the following Broth, and ſays, that he hath by Experience found it to be of marvellous Eſſicacy for hindring the forming and confirming of the Stone. Take a Cock and a Knuckle of Veal, boyl them in water with a handful of Barley, Parſley-Roots, Sorrel, Fennel, Sichory, Butchers-broom, of each an Ounce; the four cold Seeds bruiſed, of each half an Ounce; towards the end, add Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel leaves, Purſlain, Lettice, Mallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tops, and <hi>March</hi> Violets, of each half a handful; and then keep the Broth, of which the Patient for four Mornings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether faſting, ſhall take about half a Pint with a little of the Juice of a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, making it boyl one turn over the fire, every time before it be taken; you will quickly ſee, ſays he, a wonderful Operation, and it is a Medicamental Aliment.</p>
               <p>In the ſame place he gives the Receipt of a rare Powder againſt the Stone. ℞ <hi>Nucleorum meſpil.</hi> Unc. 1. <hi>Pul. elect.
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:59957:117"/>Diatrag. frigidi, Dracn.</hi> 2. <hi>Quatuor ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum frig. majorum mundatorum, gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyriſae raſae ana drac.</hi> 1. <hi>Sem. Saxif. dr.</hi> 2. <hi>Seminum milii ſolis, geniſtae, pimpinellae, bruſci &amp; aſparagi, ana Scrup.</hi> 1. <hi>Seminis Altheae, dr.</hi> 1. <hi>ſemiſ. Sacchari albiſſimi, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nc.</hi> 6. <hi>fiat pulvis.</hi> This Powder is to be taken the firſt days of the New Moon and Firſt Quarter, of the Full Moon and Laſt Quarter; and ſo for all the Months after, to the quantity of a Spoonful in the Morning three hours before eating. For the ſame Effect he preſcribes the following Powder. ℞ <hi>Coriand. praep. ſcrup.</hi> 4. <hi>Aniſi, Marathri, granor. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kekengi, Milii ſolis, ana drach</hi> 2. <hi>Zinzib. Cinnamomi, ana ſcrup.</hi> 2. <hi>Turbith Elect. drach.</hi> 1. <hi>Carvi ſcrup.</hi> 2. <hi>Galang. Nucis moſchatae, &amp; lapid. Judaici, ana ſcrup.</hi> 1. <hi>Foliorum Senae mundatorum ad duplum omnium, Diagredii dr.</hi> 2. <hi>Semiſs. miſce &amp; fiat pulvis. Doſis erit ad drach.</hi> 1. <hi>Cum vino albo. Capiat ager tribus horis ante prandium.</hi> Glyſters for aſſwaging Nephritick pains, are to be made of the Decoction of Lettice, Scariole Purſlain, the Flowers of Violets and Nenuphur.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:59957:118"/>Melilot, Camomile, Dill, the leaves of Mallows, Marſh-mallows, Bran, and Linſeed; and in the Colature is to be diſſolved cleaned Caſſia, a little Sugar, yolks of Eggs, and Turpentine, which is a Soveraign Remedy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beverovicius</hi> ſpeaks of a great many Medicines; but ſeeing he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, we ſhall here wave the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and ſpeak only of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that are uſed after the Operation, and for Remedying the Symptoms.</p>
               <p>They have nothing that is particular, but that they ought to be more moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and humectant than for the other parts. Every Chirurgeon makes his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent Powders, and other Medicines to reſiſt Putrifaction, and breeding of new Fleſh. Sometimes the Rumps of Pullets are dryed with a little Rock Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom Calcined, and ſcraped Lint; or elſe there is added to it the Powder of Burnt Lead malaxated with a very little Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palma, or <hi>de minio:</hi> A very good Epu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotick is made with an Ounce of Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pholix, half an Ounce of the Plaiſter <hi>de minio,</hi> two Drams of Rock Allom
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:59957:118"/>Calcined, all incorporate together. In like manner a very good Deſiccative may be made of Bole Armoniack and the Litharge of Gold, of each an Ounce; the Salt of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and <hi>Crollius</hi> his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamental Stone, of each a Dram; all being reduced into a Powder, they are to be made into an Unguent with a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of the Oyl of Roſes.</p>
               <p>To remove the Calloſity of Fiſtula's, one may make uſe of the Powder which is found at the bottom of Sphagedenick Water: You may take what quantity you pleaſe of that Powder, let it dry in the ſhade, and then grind it upon <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry-ſtone,</hi> or Marble; add thereto a little Water, in which Gum Arabick hath been diſſolved, and make it up into long and ſmall Trochisks of divers ſhapes.</p>
               <p>A more violent and efficacious Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick for the ſame purpoſe may be made of equal parts of Corroſive Sublimate, and Rock Allom Calcined, a little Opium and Saffron; all muſt be pounded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to give it a Body, add as much Gummed water as is neceſſary, and make it into Trochisks according to Art.</p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:59957:119"/>
               <p>We ought not to forget the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Liniment of <hi>Arceus,</hi> which in Dreſſing ſerves for a Digeſtive: Thus it is doſcribed. ℞ <hi>Gummi Elemni &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebinthinae abietinae ana <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nc.</hi> 1. <hi>Sem. ſaevi caſtrati antiqui &amp; liquefacti, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nc.</hi> 2. <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedinis Porcinae <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nc.</hi> 1. <hi>Miſce &amp; ad ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Linimentum facito. Arceus,</hi> in his firſt Book of the good Method of Curing Diſeaſes, ſays, that this Medicine is of ſo great Vertue, that with half an Ounce of it one may Cure the greateſt Wounds, provided no Accident ſupervene; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they add to it as much of the Oyl of St. <hi>Johns-wort</hi> as is thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, according to the intention that is had in uſing it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pareus</hi> gives the Deſcription of the Oyl of Eggs, <hi>pag.</hi> 752. Take the Yolks of hard Eggs, rub them betwixt your Hands, and fry them in a Frying-pan over a gentle fire, ſtir them with a ſpoon until they become red or tauny, and the Oyl come from them, then put them into a Hair-cloath, and preſs out the Oyl, as that of Almonds, and keep it for Uſe.</p>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:59957:119"/>
               <p>Here we may ſubjoyn the Deſcription of Harts-horn Jelly, which is Excellent againſt the Looſeneſs that happens to thoſe that are cut of the Stone; it is made of two Ounces of the ſhavings of Harts-horn, and as much of Ivory, which are to be boyled in a quart of Water un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Juice of them be Extracted: Then the Decoction is to be ſtrained through a Cloath, and the Colature cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the white of an Egg, adding thereto a little of the Juice of Limon, white Sugar, and Cinnamon; the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lature is to be ſet over the fire again, and when it begins to boyl, a white ſcum will riſe, then a little White-wine is to be put into it to ſettle the ſcum, and a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when the ſcum riſes again, ſome more White-wine is to be put into it; the Humidity is to be let evaporate, until one perceive that the Liquor becomes Glewy, then it is to be taken off, and quickly ſtrained through a clean Linnen Cloath, and put into Veſſels, to be kept for Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: A ſpoonful or two of it is now and then to be given to the Patient, to ſtop his Looſeneſs.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:120"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Popes Head</hi> in the <hi>Lower-walk</hi> of the <hi>New-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>AN</hi> Inſtitution of General Hiſtory; <hi>or the Hiſtory of the World. By</hi> William Howel, <hi>L. L. D. in Two Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hiſtorical Collections; <hi>or, an Exact Account of the Proceedings of the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>in Queen</hi> Elizabeth's <hi>Reign.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Journey <hi>into</hi> Greece, <hi>by</hi> George Wheeler, <abbr>
                     <hi>Eſq</hi>
                  </abbr> in Company of Dr. Spon <hi>of</hi> Lyons. <hi>In Six Books. Containing,</hi> 1. <hi>A Voyage from</hi> Venice <hi>to</hi> Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople. 2. <hi>An Account of</hi> Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>and the Adjacent Places.</hi> 3. <hi>A Voyage through the Leſſer</hi> Aſia. 4. <hi>A Voyage from</hi> Zant <hi>through ſeveral Parts of</hi> Greece <hi>to</hi> Athens. 5. <hi>An Account of</hi> Athens. 6. <hi>Several Journeys from</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, <hi>into</hi> Attica, Corinth, Boeotia, &amp;c. <hi>With variety of Sculptures.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:120"/>
               <item>Pharamond, <hi>Compleat in</hi> Engliſh, <hi>an Excellent Romance.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clelia, <hi>a Romance, in</hi> Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Partheniſſa, <hi>Compleat in</hi> Engliſh.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Hiſtorical</hi> Heroick Poem <hi>on the Life of the Right Honourable,</hi> Thomas, <hi>Earl of</hi> Oſſory, <hi>(with his Picture neatly engraven on a Copper-Plate) Written by</hi> Elkanah Settle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Proteſtant Plot no Paradox; <hi>or,</hi> Phanaticks <hi>under that Name Plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and Government.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Engliſh Jeroboam, <hi>or, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reforming Magiſtrate, and what the Church of</hi> England <hi>may expect from ſuch a one.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations Offered <hi>to all the</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations of England, <hi>containing Seaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Advice to them in their Future</hi> Elections of Burgeſſes <hi>to ſerve in</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>An</hi> Hiſtorical Relation <hi>of the Firſt Diſcovery of the Iſle of</hi> Madera.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Proteſtant Religion is a Sure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb facs="tcp:59957:121"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c. By the Right Honourable,</hi> Charles, <hi>Earl of</hi> Derby.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Jeſuits Policy <hi>to Suppreſs</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. <hi>By a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Warning Piece <hi>for the</hi> Unruly, <hi>in Two Viſitation Sermons, by</hi> Seth Buſhel, <hi>D. D.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Great Efficacy <hi>and</hi> Neceſſity <hi>of</hi> Good Example, <hi>eſpecially in the Clergy, in a Viſitation Sermon at</hi> Guilford, <hi>by</hi> Thomas Duncomb, <hi>D. D.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Sermon <hi>Preached before the King, by</hi> Miles Barn, <hi>Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Sermon <hi>Preached at the Aſſizes at</hi> Lancaſter, <hi>by</hi> Henry Piggot, <hi>B. D.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Praiſe and Adoration, <hi>a Sermon on</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Sunday, <hi>before the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity at</hi> Oxford, 1681. <hi>by</hi> Thomas Manningham, <hi>M. A. late Fellow of</hi> New-Colledge <hi>in</hi> Oxford.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> New-years-gift for the Anti-prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Men; <hi>or, a Lawyers Opinion, in Defence of His Majeſties Power-Royal, of Granting Pardons as he pleaſes; wherein is more particularly diſcuſſed the Validity of the Earl of</hi> Danby's <hi>Pardon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:121"/>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Spaniſh Hiſtory; <hi>or the Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that happened in the Court of</hi> Spain, <hi>between</hi> Don John <hi>of</hi> Auſtria, <hi>and</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Nitard: <hi>with all the Letters, and Politick Diſcourſes, relating to thoſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rapin's Reflexions <hi>on Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern</hi> Philoſophy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Engliſh Princeſs; <hi>or, the Dutcheſs Queen, a pleaſant Novel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Court</hi> Songs <hi>and</hi> Poems, <hi>being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Collection.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Temple of Death, <hi>with other</hi> Poems. <hi>By a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hogan Moganides; <hi>or, the</hi> Dutch Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibras.</item>
               <item>Liquor Alchaheſt; <hi>or, the Immortal Diſſolvent of</hi> Paracelſus <hi>and</hi> Helmont, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Philoſophical Eſſay; <hi>or, the Hiſtory of Petrification, by Dr. Sherly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gulielmus Ferrarius de bello Batavico.</item>
               <item>Weſtminſter Quibbles, <hi>very Pleaſant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Zaide; <hi>or the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Hiſtory, a Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Romance.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:122"/>
               <item>Memoirs <hi>of the Dutcheſs of</hi> Mazarine.</item>
               <item>Anima Mundi, <hi>an Hiſtorical Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Opinion of the Ancients, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Mans Soul after this Life, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to unenlightened Nature.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clarks Manual; <hi>a Book of Preſidents.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Saunders <hi>his Aſtrological Phyſick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Copy of the</hi> Two Journal Books <hi>of the</hi> Houſe of Commons, <hi>in which is the whole Hiſtory of the late horrid</hi> Popiſh Plot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Wits Paraphras'd; <hi>or, Paraphraſe upon Paraphraſe. In a Burleſque on the late ſeveral Tranſlations of</hi> Ovid's Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</item>
               <item>Two Diſcourſes; <hi>the Firſt ſhewing, how the Chief Criterions of Philoſophical Truth, invented by Speculative Men, more eminently ſerve Divine Revelation, than either Philoſophy, or Natural Religion. The Second manifeſting, how all the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Intellectual World,</hi> viz. <hi>Reaſon, Morality, Civil Government, and Religion, have been undermined by Popiſh Doctrines and Policies. By</hi> Thomas Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham, <hi>M. A. Fellow of New-Colledge in</hi> Oxford, <hi>and Rector of</hi> Eaſt Tyſted <hi>in</hi> Hantſhire.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:59957:122"/>
               <item>Machiavel Redivivus; <hi>being an Exact Diſcovery or Narrative of the Principles and Politicks of our Bejeſuited Modern</hi> Phanaticks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Preſent State of Geneva; <hi>with a brief Deſcription of that City, and the ſeveral Changes and Alterations it hath been ſubject to, from the Firſt Foundation thereof.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amarillis to Tityrus; <hi>being the Firſt Heroick Harangue of the Excellent Pen of Monſieur</hi> Scudery; <hi>a Witty and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Novel,</hi> Engliſhed <hi>by a Perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Twelves.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Amours of the</hi> Count Du Noy; <hi>a Witty Novel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Penitent Hermit; <hi>or, the Fruits of Jealouſie; a Novel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Engliſh Monſieur, <hi>a Comical No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hiſtory of the</hi> Pallas Royal; <hi>or, the Amours of the</hi> French <hi>King, and</hi> Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de la Valiere.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Amours of</hi> Madam, <hi>and the</hi> Count de Guiche.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Novels of</hi> Queen Elzabeth, <hi>in Two Parts.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:59957:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
